<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Multi-agent reinforcement learning</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2019-12-22">December 22, 2019</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Schnebli</forename><surname>Zoltan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Multi-agent reinforcement learning</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2019-12-22">December 22, 2019</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>A SURVEY OF MULTI-AGENT SYSTEMS USED FOR
AIR TRAFFICCONTROL
.=</p>
<p>Sütő Evelyne 1
.=</p>
<p>1Babeş-Bolyai University, Computer Science, Cluj-Napoca.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>INTRODUCTION
.=</p>
<p>∙ Purpose: Explore why air traffic control is an ideal system for
agent oriented implementation
.=</p>
<p>∙ Free Flight system
.=</p>
<p>∙ Present two important components of the Free flight system
.=</p>
<p>∙ Air Traffic Flow Management
.=</p>
<p>∙ Conflict resolution
.=</p>
<p>∙ Conclusions
.=</p>
<p>2.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ATC CHALLANGES.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AIR TRAFFIC CONTROL CHALLANGES
.=</p>
<p>∙ The growing air traffic since the 1990s.
∙ ATC was mainly relying on human resources to resolve the traffic
management
.=</p>
<p>∙ FAA estimates put weather, routing decisions and airport condition
induced delays at 1,682,700 h in 2007, resulting in a staggering
economic loss of over $41 billion, and in 740 million gallons of fuel
being wasted. [Agogino and Tumer, 2012]
.=</p>
<p>∙ Intelligent air traffic flow management is one of the fundamental
challenges facing the Federal Aviation Administration (FAA) today.
.=</p>
<p>4.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>WHY MULTI AGENT SYSTEMS?
.=</p>
<p>∙ ATC systems have geographically and functionally distributed
elements, subsystems which have a high degree of autonomy and
highly dynamic environment.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The system is very complex, each decision can affect other
unexpected parts of the environment.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Decentralised systems are more effective, can adapt more easily.
∙ Multi-agent systems can solve system conflict with different
policies: negotiation, competition, cooperation.
.=</p>
<p>5.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>SOLUTION: FREE FLIGHT SYSTEM
.=</p>
<p>∙ With the appearance of GPS and ADS-B devices the automation of
ATC has become more and more possible.
.=</p>
<p>∙ NASA introduced the concept of Free Flight systems to solve this
problem.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Free Flight system allows pilots to choose their own routes,
altitude and speed and essentially gives each aircraft the freedom
to self-optimise.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The goal is to create a decentralised system by using on-board
equipment which allows aircrafts to share some of the workload,
such as navigation, weather prediction and aircraft separation,
with ground controllers.
.=</p>
<p>7.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ELEMENTS OF FREE FLIGHT SYSTEMS
.=</p>
<p>∙ Air traffic flow management: the regulation of air traffic in order to
avoid exceeding airport or air traffic control capacity in handling
traffic, and to ensure that available capacity is used efficiently
.=</p>
<p>∙ Conflict resolution: resolving the problems of two aircraft
trajectories meeting in the future
.=</p>
<p>8.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AIR TRAFFIC FLOW MANAGEMENT
.=</p>
<p>Currently relies on a centralised, hierarchical routing strategy that
performs flow projections ranging from 1 to 6 hour.
.=</p>
<p>We will discuss an agent oriented system from
[Agogino and Tumer, 2012]
.=</p>
<p>9.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>COMPONENTS OF ATFM
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agents
.=</p>
<p>∙ If we used aircrafts as agents the system would become too big
.=</p>
<p>∙ Researchers use individual ground locations throughout the airspace
called ’fixes’ as agents. Each agent is then responsible for any aircraft
going through its fix.
.=</p>
<p>10.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>COMPONENTS OF ATFM
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agent actions
.=</p>
<p>∙ Miles in trail (MIT): controls the distance aircraft have to keep from
each other wile approaching a fix.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Ground delays: controls how long aircraft that will eventually go
through a fix should wait on the ground. With this action, congestion
can be reduced if some agents choose ground delays and others do
not, as this will spread out the congestion.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Routing: controls the routes of aircraft going through its fix, by diverting
them to take other routes that will (in principle) avoid the congestion.
.=</p>
<p>11.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>COMPONENTS OF ATFM
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agent learning
.=</p>
<p>∙ The agents use reinforcement learning to improve the system.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Each agent has its own reward function which they need to maximise.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The agents use the ϵ-greedy learning algorithm.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Chooses the action with the highest table value with probability 1 - ϵ
and chooses a random action with probability ϵ.
.=</p>
<p>V(a) = (1− λ)V(a) + λR
.=</p>
<p>12.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ATFM EXPERIMENTS
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agent learning
.=</p>
<p>∙ The researchers use a simulation tool called FACET (Future ATM
Concepts Evaluation Tool) to test theirs system.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The effectiveness of the system is then calculated based on the linear
combination of the amount of congestion and air traffic delay.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The agents take independent actions that maximize the system
evaluation function G(z).
.=</p>
<p>G(z) = (B(z) + αC(z))
.=</p>
<p>where B(z) is the total delay penalty for all aircraft in the system, and
C(z) is the total congestion penalty.
.=</p>
<p>13.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>CONFLICT RESOLUTION
.=</p>
<p>First we we’ll explore Distributed problem solvers for ATC
[Cammarata et al., 1988]
.=</p>
<p>∙ Each aircraft is an agent
.=</p>
<p>∙ Goal: move from point A to B which can lead to shared coflicts
.=</p>
<p>∙ Conflict arises when aircrafts enter each other’s protected zone.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agents resolve these conflicts through distributed problem solving
.=</p>
<p>14.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>CONFLICT RESOLUTION
.=</p>
<p>∙ Each system implements the information distribution policies
where the information should be sent to other aircraft selectively
.=</p>
<p>∙ An agent is selected to perform the evaluation, create a new plan
and execute it. It that’s not enough other agents replan as well
until conflict is resolved.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Usually the agent with the most degree of freedom is the chosen
planner.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The most knowledgeable agent can also be a planner.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Task sharing policy
.=</p>
<p>15.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AUTONOMOUS AGENTS FOR AIR-TRAFFIC DECONFLICTION
.=</p>
<p>Autonomous Agents for Air-Traffic Deconfliction
[Pěchouček et al., 2006]
.=</p>
<p>∙ The aircraft are modeled by agent containers hosting several
agents
.=</p>
<p>∙ The aircrafts have multiple information specific zones:
Communication, Alert, Safety and Collision zones.
.=</p>
<p>∙ The deconfliction can happen by cooperative or non-cooperative
negotiation.
.=</p>
<p>∙ When agents enter each other’s communication zones they
subscribe to the other’s flight plan updates.
.=</p>
<p>∙ At each update conflict detection is made
.=</p>
<p>16.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AUTONOMOUS AGENTS FOR AIR-TRAFFIC DECONFLICTION
.=</p>
<p>17.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AUTONOMOUS AGENTS FOR AIR-TRAFFIC DECONFLICTION
.=</p>
<p>Agents use a rule based system to modify their flight plan.
.=</p>
<p>The goal is to guarantee minimal future conflicts
.=</p>
<p>The flight plans can be described by waypoints and timestamps at
which the airplane arrives to that specific waypoint. Using these the
flight planner generates the path consisting of segments and
elements.
.=</p>
<p>18.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>AUTONOMOUS AGENTS FOR AIR-TRAFFIC DECONFLICTION
.=</p>
<p>∙ head-on collision, both of them turning to the right.
∙ rear collision, it has to change its flight plan so that it turns to the
right and passes the front airplane without endangering it.
.=</p>
<p>∙ side collision (right), The aircraft A needs to slow down its speed.
∙ side collision (left), aircraft A changes its flight plan by increasing
its flight speed so that it passes the collision point before the
airplane B.
.=</p>
<p>19.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>CONCLUSION
.=</p>
<p>∙ ATC and ATFM are very well suited for agent oriented
implementations.
.=</p>
<p>∙ Agent oriented Free flight system are easily adaptable and
improve the problems of delays and fuel waste.
.=</p>
<p>∙ We already have some good results in this automatization task,
but we still need to improve it.
.=</p>
<p>21.=</p>
</div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Agogino, A. K. and Tumer, K. (2012).
A multiagent approach to managing air traffic flow.
Autonomous Agents and Multi-Agent Systems, 24(1):1–25.
.=</p>
<p>Cammarata, S., McArthur, D., and Steeb, R. (1988).
Strategies of cooperation in distributed problem solving.
In Readings in Distributed Artificial Intelligence, pages 102–105.
Elsevier.
Pěchouček, M., Šišlák, D., Pavlíček, D., and Uller, M. (2006).
Autonomous agents for air-traffic deconfliction.
In Proceedings of the fifth international joint conference on
Autonomous agents and multiagent systems, pages 1498–1505.
ACM.
.=</p>
<p>21.=</p>
</div>
</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>


				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
