<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive XML Tree Mining on Evolving Data Streams</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2009-09-08">2009 Bled, september 8th, 2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Albert</forename><surname>Bifet</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory for Relational Algorithmics, Complexity and Learning LARCA Departament de Llenguatges i Sistemes Informàtics Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya ECML-PKDD</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ricard</forename><surname>Gavaldà</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Laboratory for Relational Algorithmics, Complexity and Learning LARCA Departament de Llenguatges i Sistemes Informàtics Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya ECML-PKDD</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Adaptive XML Tree Mining on Evolving Data Streams</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2009-09-08">2009 Bled, september 8th, 2009</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>XML Trees</head><p>&lt;?xml version= " 1 . 0 " ?&gt; &lt;?xml−s t y l e s h e e t t y p e = " t e x t / x s l " h r e f = " movie1 . x s l " ?&gt; &lt; f i l m l i b r a r y &gt; &lt;name&gt; C l a s s i c F i l m s &lt; / name&gt; &lt;movie&gt; &lt; t i t l e &gt;The B i c y c l e T h i e f &lt; / t i t l e &gt; &lt;genre&gt; S o c i a l Drama&lt; / genre&gt; &lt;language&gt; I t a l i a n &lt; / language&gt; &lt;year &gt;1948&lt; / year &gt; &lt; l e n g t h &gt;90 Min . &lt; / l e n g t h &gt; &lt; f i l m t y p e &gt;BW&lt; / f i l m t y p e &gt; &lt; c r e d i t s &gt; &lt; d i r e c t o r &gt; V i t t o r i o de Sica &lt; / d i r e c t o r &gt; &lt; s t o r y &gt;Gennarino B a r t o l i n i &lt; / s t o r y &gt; &lt;cinematography&gt; C a r l o M o n t u o r i &lt; / cinematography&gt; &lt; / c r e d i t s &gt; &lt; / movie&gt; &lt; / f i l m l i b r a r y &gt;</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Issues Pattern Classification</head><p>Mapping patterns → features Frequent patterns, closed patterns, generators, . . .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data stream classification</head><p>Highly sublinear memory (in #items seen) Low processing time per item Tolerate distribution &amp; concept change</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Our Work</head><p>To our knowledge, first tree pattern classifier in data streams Builds features by mining frequent closed subtrees or maximal subtrees Miner is interesting in itself / competititve with state-of-the art Uses recently proposed ensemble methods for classification Implementation over the MOA framework</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tree (Pattern) Mining</head><p>Task occurs in chemistry, computer vision, text retrieval bioinformatics, Web analysis, XML queries, . . . all trees whose support is no less than min_support  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition</head><p>We define the following Galois connection pair:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">For finite A ⊆ D σ (A) is the set of subtrees of the A trees in T σ (A) = {t ∈ T ∀ t ∈ A (t t )} For finite B ⊂ T τ D (B) is the set of supertrees of the B trees in D τ D (B) = {t ∈ D ∀ t ∈ B (t t )}</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Closure Operator</head><p>The composition C D = σ • τ D is a closure operator</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Characterizing closed trees</head><p>A tree t is closed (no supertree with same support) in </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Miner is interesting in itself</head><p>Can also be used for static databases For small number of labels: slightly faster than CMTreeMiner significantly less memory than CMTreeMiner (CMTreeMiner keeps all dataset in memory) T8M synthetic dataset [Zaki02]: 100 labels, mother tree size 10,000, DBsize 8M</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Maximal Trees</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Maximal Trees</head><p>A tree is maximal if no supertree of t is frequent All maximal trees are closed Non-maximal closed patterns can be derived from maximal ones </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>XML Tree Framework on evolving data streams</head><p>Two components:</p><p>An XML closed frequent tree miner A Data stream classifier algorithm, which we will feed with tuples to be classified online.</p><p>Attributes in these tuples represent the occurrence of the current closed trees in the originating tree, although the classifier algorithm need not be aware of this.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Experiments: Synthetic datasets</head><p>Zaki's tree dataset generator 2 mother trees, 2 classes, depth and fanout 10 </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A transaction supports a tree if the tree is a subtree of the transaction Support of a tree is the number of transactions that support it Given a dataset of trees and value min_support, find Frequent Tree mining (FT):</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Closed Frequent Tree mining (CT):+ no super-tree with the same support</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>D1 and D2 be two datasets of patterns. A pattern t is closed for D1 ∪ D2 if and only if Theorem Let D be a pattern dataset. A pattern t is closed for D if and only if the intersection of all its closed superpatterns is t. of B trees; Build closed tree lattice for B, L 2 ; L := merge(L,L 2 ) (using addition rule) Memory &amp; time depend on lattice size (number of closed trees) not on DB size! Efficient ops. using the representation for trees by [Balcázar-Bifet-Lozano] Dealing with time changes Keep a window on recent stream elements Actually, just its lattice of closed sets! Keep track of number of closed trees in lattice, N Use some change detector on N When change is detected: Drop stale part of the window Update lattice to reflect this deletion, using deletion rule Alternatively, sliding window of some fixed size</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure: A dataset example</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Previous Work [</head><label>Work</label><figDesc>Zaki-Agrawal] Classifier from frequent sets + Bayesian rules [Kudo et al.] Classifier from "significant" frequent trees + boosting [Collins et al.,Kashima et al.] SVM's, tree kernels; feature space = frequent trees CMTreeMiner [Chi et al.], [Termier et al.] Dryade: Closed frequent tree miners without computing all frequent trees [Li et al 06] Frequent subtree miner for XML data streams [Bifet-G 08] Frequent closed pattern miner in data streams, unlabelled trees Closure Operator on Trees D: the finite input dataset of trees T : the (infinite) set of all trees</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>1M samples, node labels change every 250,000 treesExperiments: Real dataset LOGML files [Zaki 02] describing 3 weeks of user sessions logs, each as XML file classes = .edu vs. non-.edu visitors Maximal Closed # Trees Att. Acc. Mem. Att. Acc. Mem. Conclusions A tree / XML tree stream classifier system Frequent closed / maximal trees as features Frequent closed tree miner based on closure operators That reacts quickly to distribution / label changes Maximal trees may suffice More experiments for better understanding of behavior Especially, comparison with CMTreeMiner Deletion of obsolete attributes Use generators instead of closed / maximal XML mining in data streams when #labels is large</figDesc><table>Bagging 
Time 
Acc. Mem. 

AdaTreeMiner 161.61 80.06 4.93 
IncTreeMiner 
212.75 65.73 
4.4 
CSLOG12 
15483 84 79.64 
1.2 
228 78.12 2.54 
CSLOG23 
15037 88 79.81 1.21 243 78.77 2.75 
CSLOG31 
15702 86 79.94 1.25 243 77.60 2.73 
CSLOG123 23111 84 80.02 
1.7 
228 78.91 4.18 
Future Work 

</table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">t is a closed pattern for D1, or t is a closed pattern for D2, or t is a subpattern of a closed pattern in D1 and of a closed pattern in D2 and C D 1 ∪D 2 ({t}) = {t}.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Moa (another native NZ bird) is not only flightless, like the Weka, but also extinct.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>with and without Naïve Bayes classifiers at the leaves.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
