<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Enumeration of simple complete topological graphs $</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Kynčl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Department of Applied Mathematics and Institute for Theoretical Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Faculty of Mathematics and Physics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Charles University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Malostranské nám. 25</addrLine>
									<postCode>118 00</postCode>
									<settlement>Prague</settlement>
									<country key="CZ">Czech Republic</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Enumeration of simple complete topological graphs $</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">European Journal of Combinatorics</title>
						<imprint>
							<biblScope unit="volume">30</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1676" to="1685"/>
							<date type="published" when="2009">2009</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ejc.2009.03.005</idno>
					<note type="submission">Article history: Available online 5 April 2009</note>
					<note>Contents lists available at ScienceDirect European Journal of Combinatorics journal homepage: www.elsevier.com/locate/ejc a r t i c l e i n f o</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>a b s t r a c t</head><p>A simple topological graph T = (V (T ), E(T )) is a drawing of a graph in the plane, where every two edges have at most one common point (an end-point or a crossing) and no three edges pass through a single crossing. Topological graphs G and H are isomorphic if H can be obtained from G by a homeomorphism of the sphere, and weakly isomorphic if G and H have the same set of pairs of crossing edges. We prove that the number of isomorphism classes of simple complete topological graphs on n vertices is 2 Θ(n 4 ) . We also show that the number of weak isomorphism classes of simple complete topological graphs with n vertices and n 4 crossings is at least 2 n(log n−O(1)) , which improves the estimate of Harborth and Mengersen.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p>A topological graph T = (V (T ), E(T )) is a drawing of an (abstract) graph G in the plane with the following properties. The vertices of G are represented by a set V (T ) of distinct points in the plane and the edges of G are represented by a set E(T ) of simple curves connecting the corresponding pairs of points. We call the elements of V (T ) and E(T ) vertices and edges of T . The edges cannot pass through any vertices except their end-points. Any intersection point of two edges is either a common end-point or a crossing, a point where the two edges properly cross (''touching'' of the edges is not allowed). We also require that any two edges have only finitely many intersection points and that no three edges pass through a single crossing. A topological graph is simple if every two edges have at most one common point (which is either a common end-point or a crossing). A topological graph is complete if it is a drawing of a complete graph.</p><p>We use two different notions of isomorphism to enumerate the topological graphs. Topological graphs G and H are weakly isomorphic if there exists an incidence preserving one-toone correspondence between V (G), E(G) and V (H), E(H) such that two edges of G cross if and only if the corresponding two edges of H do.</p><p>Topological graphs G and H are isomorphic if there exists a homeomorphism of the sphere which transforms G into H. (In the next section we state an equivalent combinatorial definition.)</p><p>Unlike the isomorphism, weak isomorphism can change the faces of the involved topological graphs, as well as the order in which one edge crosses other edges.</p><p>Pach and Tóth <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> proved the following lower and upper bounds on the number T w (n) of weak isomorphism classes of simple complete topological graphs on n vertices. (I have proved the same bounds in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref> by a different and more complicated method, not having been aware of this result.) Theorem 1 <ref type="bibr">([7,9]</ref>).</p><p>2 Ω(n 2 )</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">≤ T w (n) ≤ ((n − 2)!) n = 2 O(n 2 log n) .</formula><p>It is still an open problem which of these bounds is closer to the truth. More precise estimate is known for the number T ext w (n) of weak isomorphism classes of complete extendable topological graphs. A simple topological graph is called extendable if its edges can be extended to a pseudoline arrangement. A pseudoline arrangement is a collection of unbounded simple curves in the plane such that every two of the curves cross at most once and every common point of two curves is a proper crossing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 2 ([7]).</head><p>T ext</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">w (n) = 2 Θ(n 2 ) .</formula><p>The idea of the proof is the following. First, we find a close correspondence between complete extendable topological graphs on n vertices and pseudoarrangements of n points (i.e., arrangements of n points and n 2 pseudolines, where every pseudoline meets exactly two of the n points and every two pseudolines cross exactly once). Then, using the duality transform established by Goodman <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, we convert the problem into determining the number of non-isomorphic simple wiring diagrams of n pseudolines. This number is known to be of order 2 Θ(n 2 ) . (The best known upper bound, 2 0.6988·n 2 , has been established by Felsner <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>.)</p><p>It is also known that the number of weak isomorphism classes of geometric graphs (i.e., (simple) topological graphs whose edges are drawn as straight-line segments) on n vertices is 2 Θ(n log n) <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>.</p><p>We focus on enumeration with the stronger notion of isomorphism. This is motivated by earlier enumeration results for pseudoline arrangements <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>, under a similar notion of isomorphism.</p><p>Let T (n) be the the number of isomorphism classes of simple complete topological graphs. We prove the following asymptotic estimate on T (n). </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">T (n) = 2 Θ(n 4 ) .</formula><p>We also improve the estimate of Harborth and Mengersen <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> on the number T max w (n) of weak isomorphism classes of simple drawings of K n with the maximum number of crossings. They proved that T max w (n) ≥ e c √ n by considering the subgraphs formed by empty edges (i.e., the edges without crossing) and relating them with the partitions of an n-point set. Using the same construction but different enumeration method, we prove the following lower bound.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 4.</head><p>T max <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>) .</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">w (n) ≥ 2 n−5 (n − 3)! n ≥ 2 n(log n−O</formula><p>An extended abstract of this paper appeared in proceedings of Eurocomb'07 <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8]</ref>. <ref type="bibr">Theorem 3</ref> In this section we consider labeled graphs, i.e., the graphs whose vertices are distinguished by labels 1, 2, . . . , n. We require that an isomorphism of labeled graphs preserves the labels. But this makes almost no difference in the result, since the growth of the function T (n) is much faster than n!, the number of distinct labelings of n vertices. In the case of Theorem 4, however, we will have to distinguish between labeled and unlabeled graphs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Proof of</head><p>First we state some additional definitions. A rotation of a vertex v ∈ V (T ) is the clockwise cyclic order in which the edges incident with v leave the vertex v. This induces a one-to-one correspondence between the faces of G and H such that the crossings and the vertices incident with a face f of G appear along the boundary of f in the same (or inverse) cyclic order as the corresponding crossings and vertices in H appear along the boundary of the face f corresponding to f . It follows from Jordan-Schönflies theorem that this definition is equivalent to the previous one (assuming that the graphs are drawn on the sphere).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Now we establish the lower bound on T (n).</head><p>We denote by C n a complete convex geometric graph with n vertices, i.e., a complete geometric graph whose vertices are in convex position (note that all these graphs are weakly isomorphic to each other).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Theorem 5. The number of isomorphism classes of extendable graphs weakly isomorphic to C n is at least</head><p>2 Ω(n 4 ) .</p><p>Proof. For convenience, suppose that n is a multiple of 6. We partition the vertex set of the constructed graph(s) into six disjoint subsets V 0 , V 1 , . . . , V 5 , each of cardinality n 6 . For each k = 0, 1, . . . , <ref type="bibr">5,</ref> we place the vertices of the set V k on the unit circle, inside a small neighborhood of the point</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(cos( kπ 3 ), sin( kπ 3 )); see Fig. 1, left. For every two vertices u ∈ V k and v ∈ V l such that |k − l| = 3,</formula><p>we draw the edge uv as a straight-line segment. In <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>, these edges are schematically represented by the dotted corridors. For k ∈ {0, 1, 2}, the edges between the sets V k and V k+3 are drawn inside a narrow straight corridor C k connecting these two sets such that all the crossings among this group of edges occur outside the region C = C 0 ∩ C 1 ∩ C 2 , and for k, l ∈ {0, 1, 2}, k = l, all the crossings between the edges connecting V k with V k+3 and the edges connecting V l with V l+3 lie inside C . In the region C , the edges connecting V 2 with V 5 form n 2 36 parallel curves. Together with the edges connecting V 1 with V 4 , they form an n 2 36 × n 2 36 grid inside C . We partition the crossings of this grid into n 2 18 − 1 horizontal rows R i (parallel diagonals of the grid). Each (horizontal) edge e connecting V 0 with V 3 is drawn along one of the horizontal rows R i (each edge is assigned to a different row). In the neighborhood of each crossing c in R i we can decide whether the edge e passes above or below c; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_2">Fig. 1</ref>, right. These two possibilities give us two nonisomorphic graphs, and the choices can be made independently at each crossing of the grid. If we lead the horizontal edges along the middle n 2 36 rows, we can make the choice at at least n 4 1728 different crossings, which gives us at least 2 n 4 /1728 non-isomorphic extendable drawings of C n . An abstract topological graph (briefly an AT-graph) is a pair (G, R) where G is a graph and R ⊆ E(G) 2 is a set of pairs of its edges. For a topological graph T which is a drawing of G we define R T as a set of pairs of edges having at least one common crossing and we say that</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(G, R T ) is an AT-graph of T . A topological graph T is called a realization of (G, R) if R T = R. If (G, R)</formula><p>has a realization, we say that (G, R) is realizable. We say that the AT-graph (G, R) is simply realizable if it has a simple realization, i.e., a drawing which is a simple topological graph. Note that two topological graphs are weakly isomorphic if and only if they are realizations of the same abstract topological graph.</p><p>A trivial upper bound for T (n) is 2 O(n 4 log n) , since there are at most (O(n 2 ))! orders of crossings on every edge and at most 2 O(n 4 ) different extended rotation systems. In the rest of this section we improve this trivial upper bound by eliminating the 'log n' from the exponent. For extendable graphs, we can get the result directly by using the upper bound on the number of non-isomorphic arrangements of n 2 pseudolines. However, we must choose a more tricky approach for the nonextendable graphs.</p><p>We begin with a key observation which establishes a connection between simply realizable complete AT-graphs and the rotation systems of their drawings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposition 6.</head><p>(1) The rotation system of a simple complete topological graph G uniquely determines which pairs of edges of G cross, i.e., two simple complete topological graphs with the same rotation system are weakly isomorphic. (2) If two simple complete topological graphs are weakly isomorphic, then their rotation systems are either the same or inverse.</p><p>Note that these properties are a specialty of complete graphs: one rotation system may correspond to many weakly non-isomorphic non-complete simple topological graphs, and non-complete graphs can be drawn with many different rotation systems. Trivial examples of such graphs are paths and stars.</p><p>We will denote the rotation system of a topological graph G as R(G) and we will represent it as a sequence of rotations of its vertices. The rotation R(v) of a vertex v will be represented by a cyclic sequence of the labels of the remaining vertices.</p><p>The first part of this proposition, which actually establishes the upper bound on T w (n), was also proved by Pach and Tóth <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref>, and the second part was independently proved by Gioan <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. We include the proof here for completeness.</p><p>Proof. Both statements trivially hold for graphs with at most 3 vertices. Thus, we further consider only graphs with n ≥ 4 vertices.</p><p>(1) Let G be a simple complete topological graph with n vertices and the rotation system R(G).</p><p>We first observe that the AT-graph of G is uniquely determined by the AT-graphs of all 4-vertex complete subgraphs of G and that the rotation system of every subgraph of G is uniquely determined by R(G) and can be easily derived from R(G) by deleting appropriate rotations and labels.</p><p>So we only need to verify that the rotation system of a simple complete topological graph H on 4 vertices uniquely determines the AT-graph of H. There are four non-isomorphic simple drawings of K 4 with labeled vertices and they correspond exactly to the four drawings in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>. Since an isomorphism of topological graphs preserves or inverts the rotation system, each of the graphs A 4 i , i = 0, 1, 2, 3, can be drawn with exactly two mutually inverse rotation systems (either the same way as in <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref> or as a mirror image of that drawing). It remains to verify that no rotation system corresponds to more than one of the graphs A 4 i . For this purpose we list the four rotation systems of the drawings of the graphs A 4 i with the rotation (1, 2, 3) at the vertex 4: This finishes the proof of the first part of the proposition. We have also proved the second part for n = 4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Graph Rotation system</head><p>(2) It remains to prove the second statement for graphs with n ≥ 5 vertices. First we separately consider the case n = 5 and then we use it to extend the statement to graphs with more than five vertices. There are 5 non-isomorphic simple drawings of K 5 (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> or <ref type="figure" target="#fig_6">Fig. 3</ref>) and each of them is a realization of a different AT-graph (i.e., the weak isomorphism of simple drawings of K 5 implies the isomorphism). As for 4-vertex graphs, it follows that each AT-graph on 5 vertices can be drawn with only two mutually inverse rotation systems.</p><p>Let A be a simply realizable complete AT-graph with the vertex set {1, 2, . . . , n}, n ≥ 6. We know that each complete 5-vertex subgraph of A has only two possible rotation systems. Suppose that the rotation system of A[{1, 2, 3, 4, 5}], the induced subgraph of A with the vertices 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, is fixed (in some simple realization of A). We show that then the rotation system of every other 5-vertex complete subgraph of A is uniquely determined.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma. Let B and C be two 5-vertex complete subgraphs of A with exactly 4 common vertices. Then</head><formula xml:id="formula_6">α i = (α i 1 , α i 2 , . . . , α i k i ) ∈ {0, 1} k i , where α i j = 0</formula><p>if the pseudochord p r(i,j) crossing p i at c i j is oriented from the left to the right (i.e., if the rotation of c i <ref type="figure">,j)</ref> )), in the other case α i j = 1; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_7">Fig. 4</ref>. The sum of the lengths of the vectors α i is equal to n i=1 k i = 2k, but every crossing is encoded by two bits of different values. Hence, there are at most 2 k different sequences (α 1 , α 2 , . . . , α n ) encoding an arrangement with a given perimetric order and a fixed orientation of pseudochords.</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">j is (a i , a r(i,j) , b i , b r(i</formula><p>It remains to show that this encoding is injective, i.e., that we can uniquely reconstruct the isomorphism class of M from the vectors α 1 , α 2 , . . . , α n by identifying the pseudochords p r(i,j) .</p><p>We proceed by induction on k. For the arrangements without crossings there is only one isomorphism class with a fixed perimetric order. Now, suppose that we can reconstruct the isomorphism class for the arrangements with at most k − 1 crossings and take a sequence α = (α 1 , α 2 , . . . , α n ) encoding an arrangement M of oriented pseudochords {p 1 , p 2 , . . . , p n } with a given cyclic order of the end-points a i , b i , i = 1, 2, . . . , n. We can suppose that M does not contain empty pseudochords, i.e., the pseudochords without crossings (we can remove the empty pseudochords and investigate the order of crossings in the resulting arrangement M ). Each pseudochord p i divides the (topological) circle C M into two open arcs, A a i and A b i , where A a i is the arc starting at a i (and ending at b i ) in the clockwise direction. Clearly, there exists a pseudochord p i such that one of the arcs A a i , A b i contains at most one end-point of each pseudochord p j , j = i. Suppose that it is the arc A a i (the other case is symmetric). We can also suppose that all the pseudochords crossing p i start in the arc A a i (if not, we sequentially revert the orientation of each pseudochord p j ending in A a i and change the value of every bit α i j corresponding to a crossing on p j ). Let a j 1 , a j 2 , . . . , a j t be the clockwise order of the end-points of all the pseudochords crossing p i . Put j 0 = i. We observe that α j 0 = (0, 0, . . . , 0) and that α j t 1 = 1 (the pseudochord crossing p j t closest to its initial end-point a j t is one of the p j 0 , p j 1 , . . . , p j t−1 ). It follows that there exists s ∈ {0, 1, . . . , t − 1} such that α j s 1 = 0 and α j s+1 1 = 1.</p><p>Claim. The first crossing on the pseudochords p j s and p j s+1 is their common crossing, i.e., r(j s , 1) = j s+1 and r(j s+1 , 1) = j s .</p><p>Proof of Claim. The first pseudochord which crosses p j s must initiate in the arc A a js ∩ A a i . Hence, it is one of the p j s+1 , p j s+2 , . . . , p j t . For contradiction, suppose that r(j s , 1) = j s , where s ∈ {s + 2, s + 3, . . . , t}. But then the pseudochord p r(j s+1 ,1) is forced to cross p j s before p j s+1 (see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_8">Fig. 5</ref>) and then terminate in the arc A a i , which contradicts the choice of p i .</p><p>As we have identified the first crossing c = c j s 1 = c j s+1 1 on two pseudochords with adjacent initial end-points on C M , we can make an induction step and swap the end-points a j s and a j s+1 in the perimetric order of M. In this way we obtain a perimetric order inducing an arrangement with k − 1 crossings. We also delete the first value from the vectors α j s and α j s+1 and obtain an encoding α . From the induction hypothesis, α uniquely determines the isomorphism class of an arrangement M which is a ''sub-arrangement'' of M obtained from M by deleting the initial parts of p j s and p j s+1 , including their common crossing c, and redrawing C M appropriately. It follows that also the isomorphism class of M is uniquely determined by the given perimetric order and the encoding sequence α.</p><p>The following theorem together with the upper bound on T w (n) gives the upper bound on T (n) in   Let C be the boundary of D. In the neighborhood of every vertex v i we redraw a small portion of C through the interior of D such that it avoids the vertex v i , and we shorten the edges incident with v i appropriately. We obtain a topological circle C and an arrangement A G,v of O(n 3 ) pseudochords e k,j with end-points on C , which has O(n 4 ) crossings.</p><p>Clearly, we can reconstruct the original graph G from A G,v by reverting the star-cut operation, i.e., the isomorphism class of G is determined by the perimetric order and the isomorphism class of </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Graphs with maximum number of crossings</head><p>The maximum number of crossings in a simple complete topological graph with n vertices is n 4 , since every induced subgraph on four vertices has at most one crossing. An example of such a graph is the convex graph C n .</p><p>Harborth and Mengersen <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> introduced a construction of many weakly non-isomorphic simple complete topological graphs with n vertices and n 4 crossings. The construction begins with the graph G 4 = C 4 and then proceeds in n − 4 steps. In the kth step, we first select a vertex v k ∈ V (G k+3 ) and two edges e k , e k ∈ E(G k+3 ) incident with v k and adjacent in its rotation. Then, we add a new vertex w k in a small neighborhood of v k between the edges e k and e k . Finally, we draw the edges between w k and the remaining vertices of G k+3 around the vertex v k and then along the edges incident with v k so that they do not cross e k ; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_13">Fig. 7</ref>. We obtain a simple complete graph G k+4 with <ref type="bibr">k+4 4</ref> crossings.</p><p>Harborth and Mengersen <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> showed that this construction gives graphs where the subgraph formed by empty edges is almost any union of paths on n vertices, except the empty graph and the graphs with a single path having at most three edges. This yields a lower bound e Ω( √ n) on the number T max w (n).</p><p>We prove a better lower bound given by this construction by inductive enumeration of labeled graphs. The main idea is that almost every choice of the vertex v k and the edges e k , e k yields a different set of pairs of crossing edges. Proof. The theorem holds for n = 4, since there are exactly 3 weakly non-isomorphic simple drawings of K 4 with one crossing; see <ref type="figure" target="#fig_3">Fig. 2</ref>. It remains to prove that the addition of a vertex w k to the graph G k+3 in the kth step can produce at least 2(k + 3)(k + 1) weakly non-isomorphic graphs G k+4 .</p><p>Let (u 1 , u 2 , . . . , u k+2 ) be the rotation of the vertex v k in G k+3 . We claim that if v k is fixed, then each choice of the edges e k and e k yields a different weak isomorphism class of G k+4 . Suppose, without loss of generality, that e k = v k u 1 and e k = v k u k+2 . Then for each i ∈ {1, 2, . . . , k + 2}, the number of crossings of the edge v k u i with the edges incident with w k is k + 2 − i. Hence, we can uniquely determine the edges e k , e k from the AT-graph of G k+4 .</p><p>Among the edges incident with w k , the edge w k v k is always empty and the edges w k u i , where i ≥ 2, have at least one crossing. The edge w k u 1 leading close to the edge e k = v k u 1 is empty if and only if e k is empty. Hence, if e k is not empty, the AT-graph of G k+4 determines the vertex v k as the only vertex of G k+4 which is joined to w k by an empty edge. If e k is empty, the AT-graph of G k+4 gives us exactly two possibilities for the vertex v k .</p><p>There are 2(k + 3)(k + 2) different choices of the triple (v k , e k , e k ), four for every fixed edge e k .</p><p>Every simple complete topological graph with n vertices and the maximum number of crossings has at most n empty edges <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, thus there are at most 2(k + 3) pairs of triples (v k , e k , e k ) yielding two weakly isomorphic graphs G k+4 . It follows that in the kth step we can obtain at least 2(k+3)(k+2)−2(k+3) = 2(k + 3)(k + 1) weakly non-isomorphic graphs G k+4 .</p><p>By dividing the lower bound from the last theorem by n!, the number of distinct labelings of the n vertices, we directly obtain the statement of Theorem 4.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A rotation system of the topological graph T is the set of rotations of all its vertices. Similarly we define a rotation of a crossing c as the clockwise order in which the four portions of the two edges crossing at c leave the point c (note that each crossing has exactly two possible rotations). An extended rotation system of a topological graph is the set of rotations of all its vertices and crossings. Assuming that T and T are drawings of the same abstract graph, we say that their (extended) rotation systems are inverse if for each vertex v ∈ V (T ) (and each crossing c in T ) the rotation of v and the rotation of the corresponding vertex v ∈ V (T ) are inverse cyclic permutations (and so are the rotations of c and the corresponding crossing c in T ). For example, if T is a mirror image of T , then T and T have inverse (extended) rotation systems. Now we can state the combinatorial definition of the isomorphism. Topological graphs G and H are isomorphic if (1) G and H are weakly isomorphic, (2) for each edge e of G the order of crossings with the other edges of G is the same as the order of crossings on the corresponding edge e in H, and (3) the extended rotation systems of G and H are the same or inverse.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>An illustration of the proof of Theorem 5.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Drawings of all realizable AT-graphs on 4 vertices.Let V (H) = {1, 2, 3, 4}. There are exactly four distinct complete AT-graphs with the vertex set V (H) :A 4 0 = (K 4 , ∅), A 4 1 = (K 4 , {{{1, 4}, {2, 3}}}), A 4 2 = (K 4 , {{{1,3}, {2, 4}}}) and A 4 3 = (K 4 , {{{1, 2}, {3, 4}}}); see Fig. 2 for the drawings of these four graphs. Each vertex of H has two possible rotations, so there are 2 4 = 16 possible combinations of rotations. However, we show that only 8 of them are rotation systems of a simple drawing of K 4 .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the rotation system R(B) uniquely determines the rotation system R(C). Proof of Lemma. Without loss of generality, let V (B) = {1, 2, 3, 4, 5}, V (C) = {1, 2, 3, 4, 6} and let the rotation of the vertex 1 in R(B) be (2, 3, 4, 5). Then the rotation of 1 in A[{1, 2, 3, 4}] is (2, 3, 4) and it must be a subsequence of a rotation of 1 in R(C). But this always happens for exactly one of the pairs of inverse cyclic permutations of the set {2, 3, 4, 6}, thus the rotation of 1in C is uniquely determined and so is the whole rotation system of C .By repeated use of this lemma we obtain that the rotation system of every complete subgraph of A on 5 (and also 4) vertices is uniquely determined by R(A[{1, 2, 3, 4, 5}]). It remains to show</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>All five non-isomorphic simple drawings of K 5<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>An encoding of the crossings on the pseudochord p i . that this also uniquely determines the rotation of each vertex in A. But this easily follows from the fact that a cyclic order of a finite set X is uniquely determined by the cyclic order of all 3-element subsets of X (actually, it suffices to know the orders of the triples containing one fixed vertex). It follows that a simple realization of A can have only two possible rotation systems.An arrangement of pseudochords is a finite set M of simple curves in the plane with end-points on a common simple closed curve C M , such that all the curves from M lie in the region bounded by C M and every two curves in M have at most one common point, which is then a proper crossing. The elements of M are called pseudochords. The arrangement M is simple if no three pseudochords from M share a common crossing. A perimetric order of M is the counter-clockwise cyclic order of the end-points of the pseudochords of M on C M . Note that the perimetric order of M determines which pairs of pseudochords cross and which do not. Two (labeled) arrangements of pseudochords are isomorphic if they have the same perimetric order and the same orders of crossings on the corresponding pseudochords. The following proposition is a generalization of Felsner's [2] enumeration of simple wiring diagrams. Proposition 7. The number of non-isomorphic simple arrangements of n pseudochords with fixed perimetric order inducing k crossings is at most 2 k . Proof. Let M = {p 1 , p 2 , . . . , p n } be an arrangement of pseudochords with a given perimetric order. Fix an arbitrary orientation for each pseudochord p i ∈ M and denote by a i and b i its initial and terminal end-points. Further, denote by c i 1 , c i 2 , . . . , c i k i the crossings of p i with other pseudochords from M, in the order from a i to b i . To every p i we assign a vector</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>p j s cannot be the first pseudochord crossing p js .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Theorem 8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>A complete AT-graph with n vertices has at most 2 O(n 4 ) non-isomorphic simple realizations.Proof. Let G be a simple realization of a given complete AT-graph A. By Proposition 6(2), G can have two different rotation systems. Let us fix one of them. Now we introduce a star-cut representation of the graph G. Choose an arbitrary vertex v and denote by w 1 , w 2 , . . . , w n−1 the remaining vertices of G so that R(v) = (w 1 , w 2 , . . . , w n−1 ). Let S(v) denote the union of all the edges vw i of G (S(v) is a ''topological star'' with the central vertex v). If we consider</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>A simple drawing of K 5 and its star-cut representation. G drawn on the sphere S 2 , the set S 2 \ S(v) is mapped by a homeomorphism Φ onto an open regular 2(n−1)-gon D in the plane. We can visualize this by cutting the sphere along the edges of the star S(v) and then unpacking the resulting surface in the plane. The map Φ −1 can be continuously extended to the closure of D, giving a natural correspondence between the vertices and edges of D and the vertices and edges in S(v): each vertex w i corresponds to one vertex w i of D and the vertex v of G corresponds to n − 1 vertices v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v n−1 of D. If Φ preserves the orientation, the counter-clockwise order of the vertices of D is v 1 , w 1 , v 2 , w 2 , . . . , v n−1 , w n−1 . Each edge vw i ∈ E(G) splits into two adjacent edges v i w i and v i+1 w i ; see Fig. 6. During the cutting operation every edge e k of G not incident with v can be cut into several pieces. Since e k crosses each edge of S(v) at most once, it is cut into at most n pieces e k,j . Every crossing of the edge e k with an edge vw i corresponds to two end-points of two different pieces e k,j ,e k,j lying on the edges v i w i and v i+1 w i .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>A</head><label></label><figDesc>G,v and by the orientation of its edges e k,j . The arrangement A G,v has at most O(n 3 )! = 2 O(n 3 log n) different perimetric orders (including the orientations of the pseudochords) and, by Proposition 7, at most 2 O(n 4 ) different isomorphism classes. It follows that the number of non-isomorphic simple drawings of a given complete AT-graph A is at most 2 O(n 4 ) .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Extending a complete graph by a vertex w k . Theorem 9. The number of weak isomorphism classes of labeled simple complete topological graphs with n vertices and n 4 crossings is at least 2 n−5 (n − 1)!(n − 3)!.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgement</head><p>I am grateful to Pavel Valtr for introducing me to the topic of topological graphs, for many valuable comments and suggestions and for the help with the preparation of this paper.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Horizon theorems for lines and polygons</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Bern</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Eppstein</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Plassmann</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Yao</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">DIMACS Series in Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computational Science</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New Brunswick, NJ; Providence, RI</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Amer. Math. Soc</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="66" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Discrete and Computational Geometry</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the number of arrangements of pseudolines</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Felsner</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">ACM Symposium on Computational Geometry</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Philadelphia, PA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1996" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">18</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="257" to="267" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Complete graph drawings up to triangle mutations, Graph-theoretic concepts in computer science</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Gioan</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3787</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="139" to="150" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Goodman ; Grünbaum</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Sloane</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="27" to="35" />
			<date type="published" when="1980" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Drawings of the complete graph with maximum number of crossings</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Harborth</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Mengersen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of the Twenty-third Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing</title>
		<meeting>the Twenty-third Southeastern International Conference on Combinatorics, Graph Theory, and Computing<address><addrLine>Boca Raton, FL</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">88</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="225" to="228" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Knuth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Axioms and hulls</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1992" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">606</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Crossings in topological graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<pubPlace>Prague</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Charles University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
	<note type="report_type">Master Thesis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Enumeration of simple complete topological graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Electronic Notes in Discrete Mathematics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">29</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="295" to="299" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How many ways can one draw a graph? in: Graph Drawing</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Pach</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Tóth</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2912</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="58" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
