<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">The hamburger theorem</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2018-12-16">16 Dec 2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Mikio</forename><surname>Kano</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">In memory of Ferran Hurtado and Jiří Matoušek</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Jan</forename><surname>Kynčl</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">In memory of Ferran Hurtado and Jiří Matoušek</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">The hamburger theorem</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2018-12-16">16 Dec 2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-23T23:49+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Borsuk-Ulam theorem</term>
					<term>ham sandwich theorem</term>
					<term>hamburger theorem</term>
					<term>abso- lutely continuous Borel measure</term>
					<term>colored point set</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>We generalize the ham sandwich theorem to d + 1 measures on R d as follows. Let µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 be absolutely continuous finite Borel measures on R d . Let</p><p>. As a consequence we obtain that every (d + 1)-colored set of nd points in R d such that no color is used for more than n points can be partitioned into n disjoint rainbow (d − 1)-dimensional simplices.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Introduction</head><p>It is well-known that if n red points and n blue points are given in the plane in general position, then there exists a noncrossing perfect matching on these points where each edge is a straight-line segment and connects a red point with a blue point. Akiyama and Alon <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> generalized this result to higher dimensions as follows.</p><p>For a positive integer m, we write R m for the m-dimensional Euclidean space and [m] for the set {1, 2, . . . , m}.</p><p>Theorem 1 (Akiyama and Alon <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>). Let d ≥ 2 and n ≥ 2 be integers, and for each i ∈ [d], let X i be a set of n points in R d such that all X i are pairwise disjoint and no d + 1 points of X 1 ∪ X 2 ∪ · · · ∪ X d are contained in a hyperplane. Then there exist n pairwise disjoint (d−1)-dimensional simplices, each of which contains precisely one vertex from each X i , i ∈ [d].</p><p>The planar version of Theorem 1 follows, for example, from the simple fact that a shortest geometric red-blue perfect matching is noncrossing <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. This elementary metric argument does not generalize to higher dimensions, however. Akiyama and Alon <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref> proved Theorem 1 using the ham sandwich theorem; see Subsection 1.1.</p><p>Aichholzer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> and Kano, Suzuki and Uno <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> extended the planar version of Theorem 1 to an arbitrary number of colors as follows.</p><p>Theorem 2 (Aichholzer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>; Kano, Suzuki and Uno <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref>). Let r ≥ 3 and n ≥ 1 be integers. Let X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X r be r disjoint point sets in the plane. Assume that no three points of X 1 ∪ X 2 ∪ · · · ∪ X r lie on a line, r i=1 |X i | = 2n, and |X i | ≤ n for every i ∈ [r]. Then there exists a noncrossing geometric perfect matching on X 1 ∪ X 2 ∪ · · · ∪ X r where every edge connects two points from different sets X i and X j .</p><p>Aichholzer et al. <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref> proved Theorem 2 by the same metric argument as the in case of two colors. Kano, Suzuki and Uno <ref type="bibr" target="#b12">[13]</ref> first proved Theorem 2 for three colors, by induction using a result on partitions of 3-colored point sets on a line. Then they derived the case of four or more colors by merging the smallest color classes together.</p><p>Kano and Suzuki <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref> made the following conjecture generalizing Theorem 1 and Theorem 2.</p><p>Conjecture 3 (Kano and Suzuki <ref type="bibr" target="#b11">[12]</ref>). Let r ≥ d ≥ 3 and n ≥ 1 be integers. Let X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X r be r disjoint point sets in R d . Assume that no d + 1 points of X 1 ∪ X 2 ∪ · · · ∪ X r lie in a hyperplane, r i=1 |X i | = dn, and |X i | ≤ n for every i ∈ [r]. Then there exist n pairwise disjoint (d − 1)-dimensional simplices, each of them having d vertices in d distinct sets X i . Conjecture 3 holds when r = d by Theorem 1 or d = 2 by Theorem 2. In this paper we prove Conjecture 3 for every d ≥ 2 and r = d + 1. We restate it as the following theorem.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Theorem 4. Let d ≥ 2 and n ≥ 1 be integers. Let X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 be d+1 disjoint point sets in R d . Assume that no d+1 points of X 1 ∪X 2 ∪· · ·∪X d+1 lie in a hyperplane, d+1 i=1 |X i | = dn, and |X i | ≤ n for every i ∈ [d + 1]. Then there exist n pairwise disjoint (d − 1)-dimensional simplices, each of them having d vertices in d distinct sets X i .</formula><p>The proof of Theorem 4 (see Section 3) provides yet another different proof of Theorem 2. Many related results and problems on colored point sets can be found in a survey by Kaneko and Kano <ref type="bibr" target="#b10">[11]</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Simultaneous partitions of measures</head><p>We denote by S n the n-dimensional unit sphere embedded in R n+1 , that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">S n = {x ∈ R n+1 ; x = 1}.</formula><p>The Borsuk-Ulam theorem plays an important role throughout this paper. ). Let f : S n → R n be a continuous mapping. If f (−u) = −f (u) for all u ∈ S n , then there exists a point v ∈ S n such that f (v) = 0 = (0, 0, . . . , 0).</p><p>Informally speaking, the ham sandwich theorem states that a sandwich made of bread, ham and cheese can be cut by a single plane, bisecting the mass of each of the three ingredients exactly in half. According to Beyer and Zardecki <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref>, the ham sandwich theorem was conjectured by Steinhaus and appeared as Problem 123 in The Scottish Book <ref type="bibr" target="#b14">[15]</ref>. Banach gave an elementary proof of the theorem using the Borsuk-Ulam theorem for S 2 . A more direct proof can be obtained from the Borsuk-Ulam theorem for S 3 <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>. Stone and Tukey <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> generalized the ham sandwich theorem to d-dimensional sandwiches made of d ingredients as follows.</p><p>Theorem 6 (The ham sandwich theorem <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14</ref> </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(H) = µ i (R d )/2 for every i ∈ [d].</formula><p>Stone and Tukey <ref type="bibr" target="#b15">[16]</ref> proved more general versions of the ham sandwich theorem, including a version for Carathéodory outer measures and more general cutting surfaces. Cox and McKelvey <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">[6]</ref> and Hill <ref type="bibr" target="#b8">[9]</ref> generalized the ham sandwich theorem to general finite Borel measures, which include measures with finite support. For these more general measures, the condition µ i (H) = µ i (R d )/2 must be replaced by the inequality µ i (H) ≤ µ i (R d )/2. Breuer <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref> gave sufficient conditions for the existence of more general splitting ratios. In particular, he showed that for absolutely continuous measures whose supports can be separated by hyperplanes, there is a hyperplane splitting the measures in any prescribed ratio. See Matoušek's book <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref> for more generalizations of the ham sandwich theorem and other related partitioning results.</p><p>To prove Theorem 4, we follow the approach by Akiyama and Alon <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">[2]</ref>. To this end, we need to generalize the ham sandwich theorem to d+1 measures on R d . Clearly, it is not always possible to bisect all d + 1 measures by a single hyperplane, for example, if each measure is concentrated on a small ball around a different vertex of a regular simplex.</p><p>Let r ≥ d and let µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ r be finite Borel measures on R d . We say that µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ r are balanced in a subset X ⊆ R d if for every i ∈ [r], we have </p><formula xml:id="formula_3">µ i (X) ≤ 1 d · r j=1 µ j (X).</formula><formula xml:id="formula_4">µ j (H) ≥ min{1/2, 1− dω} ≥ 1/(d+ 1). Moreover, setting t = min{1/(2d), 1/d − ω} and assuming that ω d+1 = ω, the vector (µ 1 (H), µ 2 (H), . . . , µ d+1 (H)) is a convex combination of the vectors (t, t, . . . , t, 0) and (ω 1 − t, ω 2 − t, . . . , ω d − t, ω d+1 ).</formula><p>Our choice of the name for Theorem 7 is motivated by the fact that compared to a typical ham sandwich, a typical hamburger consists of more ingredients, such as bread, beef, bacon, and salad.</p><p>Note that the lower bound min{1/2, 1 − dω} on the total measure of the two halfspaces is tight: consider, for example, d + 1 measures such that each of them is concentrated on a small ball centered at a different vertex of the unit d-dimensional simplex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Proof of the hamburger theorem</head><p>In this section we prove Theorem 7. We follow the proof of the ham sandwich theorem for measures from <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><p>The set of open half-spaces in R d , together with the empty set and the whole space R d , has a natural topology of the sphere S d . We use the following parametrization.</p><p>Let u = (u 0 , u 1 , . . . , u d ) be a point from the sphere S d , that is, u 2 0 + u 2 1 + · · · + u 2 d = 1. If |u 0 | &lt; 1, then at least one of the coordinates u 1 , u 2 , . . . , u d is nonzero, and we define two halfspaces as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">H − (u) = {(x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x d ) ∈ R d ; u 1 x 1 + u 2 x 2 + · · · + u d x d &lt; u 0 }, H + (u) = {(x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x d ) ∈ R d ; u 1 x 1 + u 2 x 2 + · · · + u d x d &gt; u 0 }.</formula><p>We also define a hyperplane h(u) as the common boundary of H − (u) and H + (u). For the two remaining points (1, 0, . . . , 0) and (−1, 0, . . . , 0), we set</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">H − (1, 0, 0, . . . , 0) = R d , H + (1, 0, 0, . . . , 0) = ∅, H − (−1, 0, 0, . . . , 0) = ∅, H + (−1, 0, 0, . . . , 0) = R d .</formula><p>Note that antipodal points on S d correspond to complementary half-spaces; that is,</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">H − (u) = H + (−u) for every u ∈ S d .</formula><p>We</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">define a function f = (f 1 , f 2 , . . . , f d+1 ) : S d → R d+1 by f i (u) = µ i (H − (u)).</formula><p>Since the measures µ i are absolutely continuous, µ i (h(u)) = 0 for every hyperplane h(u).</p><p>This implies that f is continuous <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">[14]</ref>.</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">The image of f lies in the box B = d+1 i=1 [0, ω i ]</formula><p>. Moreover, f maps antipodal points of the sphere to points symmetric about the center of B. The target polytope is the subset of points (y 1 , y 2 , . . . , y d+1 ) of B satisfying the inequalities</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">y i ≤ 1 d · d+1 j=1 y j and ω i − y i ≤ 1 d · d+1 j=1 (ω j − y j ).<label>(1)</label></formula><p>See <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, left. The subset of the target polytope satisfying the inequalities</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">min{1/2, 1 − dω} ≤ y 1 + y 2 + · · · + y d+1 ≤ 1 − min{1/2, 1 − dω}<label>(2)</label></formula><p>is called the truncated target polytope; see <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>, right. Our goal is to show that the image of f intersects the truncated target polytope. We first show a proof using the notion of a degree of a map between spheres. Then we modify it so that it uses only the Borsuk-Ulam theorem. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>: Left: the target polytope inside B for d = 2 and ω 1 = ω 2 = ω 3 = 1/3. Right: the truncated target polytope corresponding to hyperplanes cutting at least 1/3 of the total measure on both sides. The segment ac, which is the intersection of the line ℓ with B, is contained in the truncated target polytope. <ref type="formula" target="#formula_10">(1)</ref> and <ref type="formula" target="#formula_11">(2)</ref> and thus it belongs to the truncated target polytope. Hence, if 0 is in the image of g, then any hyperplane h(u) such that g(u) = 0 satisfies the theorem.</p><formula xml:id="formula_12">(0, 0, 0) (ω 1 , ω 2 , ω 3 ) B ℓ a c</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">Let b = (ω 1 /2, ω 2 /2, . . . , ω d+1 /2) be the center of B. The map g = f −b is antipodal, that is, g(−u) = −g(u) for every u ∈ S d . Clearly, b satisfies both</formula><p>For the rest of the proof we may assume that 0 is not in the image of g. Then we can define an antipodal mapg :</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">S d → S d as g(u) = g(u) g(u) .</formula><p>Using the fact that every antipodal map from S d to itself has odd degree [8, Proposition 2B.6.], we conclude thatg is surjective. Hence, the image of g intersects every line passing through the origin, equivalently, the image of f intersects every line passing through b. Therefore, it is sufficient to find a line ℓ through b such that ℓ∩B belongs to the truncated target polytope. Without loss of generality, we may assume that ω 1 ≥ ω 2 ≥ · · · ≥ ω d+1 = ω. Let</p><formula xml:id="formula_15">t = min 1 2d , 1 d − ω d+1 .</formula><p>We define ℓ as the line containing the points a = (t, t, . . . , t, 0) and</p><formula xml:id="formula_16">c = (ω 1 − t, ω 2 − t, . . . , ω d − t, ω d+1 ).</formula><p>Since the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in R d , we</p><formula xml:id="formula_17">have ω i ≤ 1/d for all i ∈ [d + 1].</formula><p>Thus ω d + ω d+1 = 1 − (ω 1 + ω 2 + · · · + ω d−1 ) ≥ 1/d and consequently ω d ≥ 1/(2d) ≥ t. This implies that both points a and c lie in B. Moreover, a and c lie on the opposite facets of B and they are symmetric around the center b. The points a and c both satisfy (1) since</p><formula xml:id="formula_18">(ω 1 − t) + (ω 2 − t) + · · · + (ω d − t) + ω d+1 = 1 − dt ≥ dω d+1 .</formula><p>They also both satisfy (2) since dt ≤ 1 − dt. Therefore, the segment ac is the intersection of the line ℓ with B and it is contained in the truncated target polytope. Now we show how to replace the degree argument with the application of the Borsuk-Ulam theorem. Let π ℓ be a projection of R d+1 in the direction of the line ℓ to a d-dimensional subspace orthogonal to ℓ, which we identify with R d . Define a map g ′ : S d → R d by g ′ (u) = π ℓ (g(u)). The map g ′ is antipodal, and so by the Borsuk-Ulam theorem, there exists u ∈ S d such that g ′ (u) = 0, which means that f (u) ∈ ℓ. This concludes the proof.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">A discrete version of the hamburger theorem</head><p>Theorem 4 follows by induction from the following discrete analogue of the hamburger theorem.</p><p>We say that point sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X r are balanced in a subset S ⊆ R d if for every i ∈ [r], we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_19">|S ∩ X i | ≤ 1 d · r j=1</formula><p>|S ∩ X j |.</p><p>Theorem 8. Let d ≥ 2 and n ≥ 2 be integers. Let X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 ⊂ R d be d + 1 disjoint point sets balanced in R d . Assume that no d + 1 points of X 1 ∪ X 2 ∪ · · · ∪ X d+1 lie in a hyperplane and that d+1 i=1 |X i | = dn. Then there exists a hyperplane h disjoint with each X i such that for each open halfspace H determined by h, the sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 are balanced in H and d+1 i=1 |H ∩ X i | is a positive integer multiple of d.</p><p>While preparing the final version of this paper, we have learned that Biniaz, Maheshwari, Nandy and Smid <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref> independently proved the plane version of Theorem 8, and they gave a linear-time algorithm for computing the cutting line.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Proof of Theorem 8</head><p>Approximating point sets by measures. Let X = d+1 i=1 X i . Replace each point p ∈ X by an open ball B(p) of a sufficiently small radius δ &gt; 0 centered in p, so that no hyperplane intersects more than d of these balls. We will apply the hamburger theorem for suitably defined measures supported by the balls B(p). Rather than taking the same measure for each of the balls, we use a variation of the trick used by Elton and Hill <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">[7]</ref>. For each p ∈ X and k ≥ 1, we choose a number β k (p) ∈ (1 − 1/k, 1 + 1/k) so that the following two conditions are satisfied. I) For every i ∈ [d + 1], we have p∈X i β k (p) = |X i |.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II) Let</head><formula xml:id="formula_20">ω i = |X i |/|X| for i ∈ [d + 1], suppose that ω d+1 = min{ω i ; i ∈ [d + 1]} and let t = min{1/(2d), 1/d − ω d+1 }.</formula><p>For every i, j ∈ [d + 1], i = j, and for every pair of proper nonempty subsets Y ⊂ X i and Z ⊂ X j , there is no vector (γ 1 , γ 2 , . . . , γ d+1 ) ∈ R d+1 that is a convex combination of the vectors (t, t, . . . , t, 0) and (ω 1 − t, ω 2 − t, . . . , ω d − t, ω d+1 ) and satisfies γ i = p∈Y β k (p) and γ j = p∈Z β k (p). Now let k ≥ 1 be a fixed integer. For each i ∈ [d + 1], let µ i,k be the measure supported by the closure of p∈X i B(p) such that it is uniform (that is, equal to a multiple of the Lebesgue measure) on each of the balls B(p) and µ i,k (B(p)) = β k (p).</p><p>Applying the hamburger theorem and a final rounding step. By condition I), the measures µ 1,k , µ 2,k , . . . , µ d+1,k are balanced in R d . We may thus apply the hamburger theorem to the normalized collection of measures µ i,k /|X|. Let h k be the resulting hyperplane. We distinguish two cases. 1) We have µ i,k (H) = 0 for some i ∈ [d+1] and some halfspace H determined by h k . Since the measures µ 1,k , µ 2,k , . . . , µ d+1,k are balanced in H, there is an α &gt; 0 such that µ j,k (H) = α for every j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}.</p><p>2) The hyperplane h k splits each measure µ i,k in a nontrivial way. By condition II), h k intersects the support of exactly d of the measures µ i,k .</p><p>For each i ∈ [d + 1], let µ i be the limit of the measures µ i,k when k grows to infinity; that is, µ i is uniform on every ball B(p) such that p ∈ X i and µ i (B(p)) = 1. Since the supports of all the measures µ i,k are uniformly bounded, there is an increasing sequence {k m ; m = 1, 2, . . . } such that the sequence of hyperplanes h km has a limit h ′ . More precisely,</p><formula xml:id="formula_21">if h km = {x ∈ R d ; x · v m = c m } where v m ∈ S d−1 , then h ′ = {x ∈ R d ; x · v = c}</formula><p>where v = lim m→∞ v m and c = lim m→∞ c m . By the absolute continuity of the measures, the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in each of the two halfspaces determined by h ′ , and the total measure d+1 j=1 µ j of each of the two halfspaces is at least n/(d + 1). One of the cases 1) or 2) occurred for infinitely many hyperplanes h km , m ≥ 1. We distinguish the two possibilities.</p><p>Suppose that case 1) occurred infinitely many times. For each m ≥ 1, let In particular, the sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 are balanced inH and 0 &lt; |H ∩ X| = d⌈α⌉ &lt; dn. It remains to show that X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 are also balanced inH ′ . Let H ′ be the open halfspace opposite to H. Since the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in H ′ , for each k ∈ [d+1]\{i} we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_22">H + km = {x ∈ R d ; x · v m &gt; c m } and H − km = {x ∈ R d ; x · v m &lt; c m } be</formula><formula xml:id="formula_23">µ k (H ′ ) = (α − ⌈α⌉) + µ k (H ′ ) ≤ (α − ⌈α⌉) + 1 d · d+1 j=1 µ j (H ′ ) = 1 d · d+1 j=1 µ j (H ′ ),</formula><p>and for the measure µ i we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_24">µ i (H ′ ) = µ i (H ′ ) ≤ 1 d · d+1 j=1 µ j (H ′ ) = 1 d ·   d+1 j=1 µ j (H ′ )   + (⌈α⌉ − α) = (n − ⌈α⌉) + (⌈α⌉ − α) = n − α.</formula><p>Since µ i (H ′ ) = |X i |, we can replace the upper bound by the nearest integer, and thus we have</p><formula xml:id="formula_25">µ i (H ′ ) ≤ n − ⌈α⌉ = 1 d · d+1 j=1 µ j (H ′ ).</formula><p>Finally, suppose that case 2) occurred infinitely many times. There is an i ∈ [d + 1] such that for infinitely many m ≥ 1, the hyperplane h km intersects the support of each measure µ j,km , j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}. In particular, for each j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, there is a point p j ∈ X j such that for infinitely many m ≥ 1, the hyperplane h km intersects each of the balls B(p j ). It follows that h ′ intersects or touches each of the balls B(p j ). Moreover, each of the halfspaces determined by h ′ contains at least one point of X i .</p><p>We now rotate the hyperplane h ′ slightly, to a hyperplane h that touches each of the balls B(p j ) with j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, so that the point sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 are balanced in each halfspace determined by h and the number of points of X in each halfspace is divisible by d. Each of the two halfspaces will still contain a positive number of points from X i , so the resulting partition of X will be nontrivial. Essentially, for each point p j , j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, we can decide independently on which side of h it will end, thus we are choosing one of 2 d possible rotations. Let Y = {p j ; j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}} be the set of these d "movable" points.</p><p>Let H ′ A and H ′ B be the two open halfspaces determined by h ′ . We may consider h ′ to be horizontal, H ′ A to be the halfspace above h ′ and H ′ B the halfspace below h ′ . We now count the points of X \ Y , which will remain above both h ′ and h or below both h ′ and h, no matter which rotation of h ′ we choose. For each j ∈</p><formula xml:id="formula_26">[d + 1] \ {i}, let a ′ j = |(X j \ {p j }) ∩ H ′ A | and b ′ j = |(X j \ {p j }) ∩ H ′ B |. Let a ′ i = |X i ∩ H ′ A | and b ′ i = |X i ∩ H ′ B |. Clearly, we have |X j | = a ′ j + b ′ j + 1 if j = i and |X i | = a ′ i + b ′ i . Finally, let a ′ = |(X \ Y ) ∩ H ′ A | and b ′ = |(X \ Y ) ∩ H ′ B |. Clearly, we have a ′ = d+1 j=1 a ′ j , b ′ = d+1 j=1 b ′ j and a ′ + b ′ = d(n − 1). For each j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, let α j = µ j (B(p j ) ∩ H ′ A ), and let α = j∈[d+1]\{i} α j . Clearly, we have 0 ≤ α j ≤ 1, 0 ≤ α ≤ d, µ j (H ′ A ) = a ′ j + α j , µ j (H ′ B ) = b ′ j + 1 − α j , the total measure d+1 j=1 µ j of H ′ A is equal to a ′ + α, and the total measure of H ′ B is equal to b ′ + d − α. Let m A = max{a ′ j ; j ∈ [d + 1]} and m B = max{b ′ j ; j ∈ [d + 1]}.</formula><p>Since the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in H ′ A and also in H ′ B , we have dm A ≤ a ′ +α and dm B ≤ b ′ +d−α, which implies that m A + m B ≤ n.</p><p>To get a positive integer multiple of the points of X in each halfspace determined by h, the numbers of points of Y that have to be moved above and below h are uniquely determined, except in the case when a ′ and b ′ are both divisible by d, in which case either all points of Y have to be moved above h or all below h. We consider this case separately.</p><p>Assume that a ′ and b ′ are both divisible by d; that is, a ′ = dn ′ A and b ′ = dn ′ B for some positive integers n ′ A , n ′ B . If α = 0 or α = d, the hyperplane h ′ already satisfies the conditions of the theorem and we can put h = h ′ . If α ∈ (0, d), then m A ≤ n ′ A and m B ≤ n ′ B . In this case, we can move all the points of Y above h (alternatively, all below h). Then there will be exactly d(n ′ A + 1) points of X above h, dn ′ B points of X below h, and each X j will have at most n ′ A + 1 points above h and at most n ′ B points below h. Thus h will satisfy the conditions of the theorem.</p><p>For the rest of the proof, assume that a ′ and b ′ are not divisible by d, and let r = b ′ mod d. Then exactly d − r points of Y have to be moved below h and the remaining r points above h.</p><p>If m A + m B = n, then necessarily dm A = a ′ + α, dm B = b ′ + d − α and r = α. We need to select a subset of r points of Y that will be moved above h, so that each X j has still at most m A points above h, and similarly with points that are moved below h. For j ∈ [d + 1], call a point set X j saturated from above if a ′ j = m A , and saturated from below if b ′ j = m B . For j = i, the set X j cannot be saturated both from above and below, since</p><formula xml:id="formula_27">a ′ j + b ′ j = |X j | − 1 ≤ n − 1 = m A + m B − 1.</formula><p>If X j is not saturated from above, we can move p j above h, and if X j is not saturated from below, we can move p j below h. It remains to verify that among the sets X j , j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, at most r = α of them are saturated from below and at most d − r = d − α of them saturated from above. This follows from the facts that if X j is saturated from above and j = i, then α j = 0; and similarly, if X j is saturated from below and j = i, then 1 − α j = 0. Now assume that m A + m B ≤ n − 1. In this case we have dm A ≤ a ′ or dm B ≤ b ′ . By symmetry, we may assume that dm B ≤ b ′ , which implies a stronger inequality d(m B + 1) ≤ b ′ − r + d. This means that we can move an arbitrary subset of d − r points of Y below h to keep the point sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 balanced in the halfspace below h. Since dm A ≤ a ′ + α, we have da ′ i ≤ a ′ + r. For j ∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, call a point set X j saturated from above if da ′ j = a ′ + r. Let s be the number of the sets X j , j = i, that are saturated from above. We need to verify that s ≤ d − r. If X j is saturated from above then a ′ j = m A and thus r ≤ α. Furthermore, for such X j we have d(a ′ j + α j ) ≤ a ′ + α, which implies α j ≤ (α − r)/d. Hence,</p><formula xml:id="formula_28">α = j∈[d+1]\{i} α j ≤ s(α − r)/d + d − s = d − s(d + r − α)/d.</formula><p>Using the inequalities 0 &lt; r ≤ α ≤ d, this further implies</p><formula xml:id="formula_29">s ≤ d 2 − dα d + r − α ≤ d 2 − dα + r(α − r) d + r − α = (d + r − α)(d − r) d + r − α = d − r.</formula><p>Therefore we can move r points from Y above h to keep the point sets X 1 , X 2 , . . . , X d+1 balanced in the halfspace above h.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Concluding remarks</head><p>We were not able to generalize the hamburger theorem for d ≥ 3 and d + 2 or more measures on R d , even if instead of the condition that the hyperplane cuts at least 1/(d + 1) of the total measure on each side, we require only that the partition is nontrivial. It is easy to see that for a given d, it would be sufficient to prove Problem 9 for r ≤ 2d − 1. Indeed, suppose that r ≥ 2d and that µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ r are measures balanced in R d . If µ 1 (R d ) ≥ µ 2 (R d ) ≥ · · · ≥ µ r (R d ), then after replacing µ r−1 and µ r by a single measure µ ′ r−1 = µ r−1 + µ r , the resulting set of r − 1 measures is still balanced in R d . For the case of five measures on R 3 , our approach from the proof of the hamburger theorem fails for the following reason. If µ i (R 3 ) = 1/5 for each i ∈ <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5]</ref>, then the target polytope, now in R 5 , intersected with the boundary of the box B, does not contain a closed curve symmetric with respect to the center of B. If such a curve existed, we could apply a generalization of the Borsuk-Ulam theorem saying that if f : S k → S k+l and g : S l → S k+l are antipodal maps, then their images intersect [14, Exercise 3. * /116].</p><p>Update. After finishing this paper, Dömötör Pálvölgyi gave a negative solution to Problem 9 for d ≥ 4 by the following construction, which we include here with his permission. Take a d-dimensional simplex with vertices v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v d+1 centered at the origin, and for each i ∈ [d + 1], let µ i be a probabilistic measure concentrated on a small ball centered at v i . Let µ d+2 be a probabilistic measure concentrated on d + 1 small balls centered at the vertices 2v 1 , 2v 2 , . . . , 2v d+1 of a larger simplex, such that for each i ∈ [d + 1], the ball centered at 2v i has measure 1/(d + 1).</p><p>For the case d = 3 and r = 5, we only have a construction showing that a constant positive fraction of the total measure in each halfspace cannot be guaranteed. Consider a simplex with vertices v 1 , v 2 , v 3 , v 4 , and for each i ∈ <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">[4]</ref>, let µ i be a measure concentrated on a small ball B i centered at v i such that µ i (B i ) = 1 + ε. Let µ 5 be a measure concentrated on a small ball B 5 centered at the origin such that µ 5 (B 5 ) = 2 − 4ε. For every hyperplane h satisfying the conditions of Problem 9, h must be disjoint with B 5 and so at least one halfspace determined by h has total measure at most 9ε.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>A noncrossing geometric properly colored perfect matching.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the two open halfspaces determined by h km . There is an i ∈ [d + 1] such that µ i,km (H + km ) = 0 occurred for infinitely many m ≥ 1 or µ i,km (H − km ) = 0 occurred for infinitely many m ≥ 1. By the absolute continuity of the measures, there is an α ≥ n/(d + 1) &gt; 0 such that for one of the halfspaces H determined by h ′ and for every j∈ [d + 1] \ {i}, we have µ j (H) = α.If h ′ is disjoint from all the balls B(p), p ∈ X, then this hyperplane satisfies the conditions of the theorem. Otherwise, h ′ intersects one ball from the support of each of the measures µ j , j ∈ [d+1]\{i}. Let h be the translation of h ′ that touches each of these d balls and such that h is in the complement of H. LetH be the open halfspace determined by h containing H, and let H ′ be the open halfspace opposite toH. Then for every j ∈ [d+1]\{i}, we have µ j (H) = ⌈α⌉.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head>Theorem 5 (</head><label>5</label><figDesc>The Borsuk-Ulam theorem [14, Theorem 2.1.1]</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, µ d be d absolutely continuous finite Borel measures on R d . Then there exists a hyperplane h such that each open halfspace H defined by h satisfies µ i</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Then there exists a hyperplane h such that for each open halfspace H defined by h, the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in H and d+1 j=1</figDesc><table>Theorem 7 (The hamburger theorem). Let d ≥ 2 be an integer. Let µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 be 
absolutely continuous finite Borel measures on R d . Let ω i = µ i (R d ) for i ∈ [d + 1] and 
ω = min{ω i ; i ∈ [d + 1]}. Assume that d+1 
j=1 ω j = 1 and that µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ d+1 are balanced in 
R d . </table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Problem 9. Let d ≥ 3 and r ≥ d + 2 be integers. Let µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ r be absolutely continuous positive finite Borel measures on R d that are balanced in R d . Does there exists a hyperplane h such that for each open halfspace H defined by h, the total measure r j=1 µ j (H) is positive and the measures µ 1 , µ 2 , . . . , µ r are balanced in H?</figDesc><table></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>We thank János Pach and the members of the DCG group at EPFL for helpful discussions. We also thank Seunghun Lee for finding an error in the previous proof of Theorem 8.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Edge-removal and non-crossing configurations in geometric graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">O</forename><surname>Aichholzer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cabello</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Fabila-Monroy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Flores-Peñaloza</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hackl</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Huemer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Hurtado</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Wood</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete Math. Theor. Comput. Sci</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="86" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Akiyama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Alon</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Combinatorial Mathematics: Proceedings of the Third International Conference</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York; Ann; New York Acad; New York</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1985" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">555</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sci.</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The early history of the ham sandwich theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Beyer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Zardecki</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Math. Monthly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="61" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">An optimal algorithm for plane matchings in multipartite geometric graphs, Algorithms and Data Structures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Biniaz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Maheshwari</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Nandy</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Smid</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9214</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="78" />
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Uneven splitting of ham sandwiches</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Breuer</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete Comput. Geom</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">43</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="876" to="892" />
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A ham sandwich theorem for general measures</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mckelvey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Social Choice and Welfare</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="75" to="83" />
			<date type="published" when="1984" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A stronger conclusion to the classical ham sandwich theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Elton</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">European J. Combin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="657" to="661" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Hatcher</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Algebraic topology</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2002" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Common hyperplane medians for random vectors</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Hill</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Amer. Math. Monthly</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">95</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="437" to="441" />
			<date type="published" when="1988" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On the maximum degree of bipartite embeddings of trees in the plane</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaneko</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Discrete and computational geometry</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">1763</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="166" to="171" />
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Discrete geometry on red and blue points in the plane -a survey -, Discrete and Computational Geometry</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Kaneko</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kano</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Algorithms and Combinatorics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="551" to="570" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>personal communication</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Properly colored geometric matchings and 3-trees without crossings on multicolored points in the plane, Discrete and Computational Geometry and Graphs</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Kano</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Suzuki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Uno</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">8845</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="111" />
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
			<publisher>Springer</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Using the Borsuk-Ulam theorem</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Matoušek</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lectures on topological methods in combinatorics and geometry, written in cooperation with Anders Björner and Günter M. Ziegler, Universitext</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>Berlin</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The Scottish Book, Mathematics from the Scottish Café, Including selected papers presented at the Scottish Book Conference</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Mauldin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Ed</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1979-05" />
			<publisher>Birkhäuser</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Denton, Tex; Boston, Mass</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>North Texas State University</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Generalized &quot;sandwich&quot; theorems</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Stone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Tukey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Duke Math. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="356" to="359" />
			<date type="published" when="1942" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
