<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Bidding Clubs a subset of a talk given at Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Leyton-Brown</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Yoav</forename><surname>Shoham</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Moshe</forename><surname>Tennenholtz</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Bidding Clubs a subset of a talk given at Infonomics Workshop, Maastricht</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:31+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What kind of intelligent system could help bidders in an auction?</head><p>proxy bidders <ref type="bibr">(eBay, etc.)</ref> really just transform English into 2 nd -price auction automation aggregation of information from different auctions bidding advice, decision support bidding clubs instead of helping one user, help a group aggregate bidders' market power unlike "buyer clubs", bidders' interests not aligned self-enforcing collusive agreement: increase expected utility</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collusion Example</head><p>Imagine a first-price auction with 6 bidders, 3 of whom decide to collude in advance Is there a pre-agreement that can benefit some, but penalize none? Naïve proposal: each bidder submits her valuation the two low bidders drop out the bidder with the highest valuation bids lower in the main auction Bidders have an incentive to lie in the pre-auction! this is true even if the high bidder pays the other two to drop out Bidding Clubs * with Y. Shoham, M. Tennenholtz <ref type="bibr">(EC'00)</ref> Bidders: N = {1, 2, …, n}: a set of bidders who will participate in an auction, A G ⊂ N: a set of bidders who are invited to participate in a pre-auction Coordinator c:</p><p>Can c hold a pre-auction that will benefit some of G and penalize none?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumptions: Coordinator</head><p>The coordinator: invites some subset of bidders to participate non-binding invitation may enforce payments from, between bidders cannot cost money to operate acts only as a representative of bidders why can it be trusted to act reliably? one way of looking at it is that c combines with A to form a new mechanism c's behavior is fully specified, common knowledge</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Assumptions: Bidders</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">IPV model, no externalities IID from distribution F First-price auction equilibrium bid: b(F, n, v) F regular: b(F, n+1, v i ) &gt; b(F, n, v i ), n ≥ 2</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deviation from standard GT setting</head><p>Uninvited agents are not aware of the possibility of the existence of a coordinator they believe that each bid placed corresponds to a single bidder they may be wrong about the number of bidders "actually" participating in auction Is this realistic? Maybe so for electronic auctions.</p><p>Equilibrium concept "Bayes-Nash with misconceptions" </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second-Price Auction: Protocol</head><p>* in the spirit of <ref type="bibr">Graham &amp; Marshall, 1987</ref> A utility-improving coordinator exists for second-price auctions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>Agents from G submit valuations to coordinator c 2.</p><p>If any agent chose not to participate:</p><p>submit a bid for each agent i who did elect to participate with price offer v i , and end the protocol 3.</p><p>Let v 1 , v 2 be the two highest valuations announced, by agent 1 and agent 2 respectively 4.</p><p>Only agent 1 is represented in the main auction, with a bid of v 1 5.</p><p>If agent 1 wins, he must pay v sec to the auctioneer and max(v 2v sec , 0) to c 6. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>First-Price Auction: Protocol</head><p>A utility-improving coordinator exists for first-price auctions 1.</p><p>Agents from G submit valuations to c 2.</p><p>If any agent declined to participate submit a bid for each agent i who did elect to participate with price offer b(F, n, v i ), and end the protocol c gives a payment of p to all agents in G Calculating p Assume agents truthful, participate</p><p>Taking into account only n, |G|, F, it is possible for c to calculate his expected gain, g c gains b(F, n, v 1 ) -b(F, m, v 1 ) whenever the globally highest bidder is a member of G Pick any s ≥ |G|; set p = g/s as before</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>bid for (only) the bidder from G with the highest valuation, of b(F, m, v 1 ), m = n -|G| + 1 4.If he wins, his payment to c is b(F, n, v 1 ) -b(F, m, v 1 ) 5.</figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Why this works</head><p>Incentive Compatibility:</p><p>With p = 0, the allocation rule and payment rule are exactly the same as in second-price auction the standard argument for incentive compatibility applies p does not depend on agents' declarations, so this payment does not affect agents' strategies The bidding club increases agents' expected gain Exactly the same outcome as in second-price auction But: all bidders receive an additional payment of p &gt; 0 Declining participation is not informative:</p><p>All bidders from G will bid their valuations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Observations</head><p>The coordinator's maximum loss in a given round is |G|p = |G|g/s. Since s may be arbitrarily big, maximum loss may be set arbitrarily close to 0 c keeps all but an arbitrarily small fraction of g Efficiency of the auction is preserved </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
