<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">6 th Annual Canadian 16ième conférence canadienne Conference on annuelle sur Intelligent Systems les systèmes intelligents Computers and Markets: Multi Agent Systems Interface between game theory/microeconomics computer science Defining characteristic: tackling both computational and incentive problems that arise when multiple self-interested agents interact Constraints from Game Theory/Microeconomics Agents self-motivated</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Leyton-Brown</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">University of British Columbia</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">6 th Annual Canadian 16ième conférence canadienne Conference on annuelle sur Intelligent Systems les systèmes intelligents Computers and Markets: Multi Agent Systems Interface between game theory/microeconomics computer science Defining characteristic: tackling both computational and incentive problems that arise when multiple self-interested agents interact Constraints from Game Theory/Microeconomics Agents self-motivated</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Exploring the Intersection of Computer Science, Microeconomics and Game Theory</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-23T23:48+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Game Theory</head><p>Mathematical study of interaction between self-interested, rational agents Game:</p><p>players/agents actions payoffs Strategies: pure strategy: picking a single action mixed strategy: randomizing over actions</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Game Theory</head><p>Consider this situation as a two-player game:</p><p>both use a correct implementation: both get 1 ms delay one correct, one defective: 4 ms delay for correct, 0 ms for defective both defective: both get a 3 ms delay.</p><p>Should you send your packets using correctly-implemented TCP (which has a "backoff" mechanism) or using a defective implementation (which doesn't)?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analyzing Games</head><p>TCP backoff game is a Prisoner's Dilemma both players have a dominant strategy: defective if player 2 plays C, D is player 1's best response if player 2 plays D, D is player 1's best response likewise for player 2 Not all games are so simple to analyze the best thing for one player to do can depend on what the other player does rock-paper-scissors poker What can we say about such games?</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Game Theory</head><p>Key insight: don't just think about single players' actions find strategy profiles where all players simultaneously play best responses Such a strategy profile is called a Nash equilibrium at least one Nash equilibrium exists in every finite game as long as agents are allowed to randomize their strategies best known algorithms for finding Nash equilibrium require exponential time</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scaling up</head><p>When we use game theory to model real systems, it's usually necessary to consider many more than two agents and actions They're big ($$$) and the internet is changing the way they're used Auctions A broader category than often perceived Generally, auctions are markets in which: agents make binding declarations of interest in one or more resources these resources are allocated according to known rules payments to/from agents may be imposed Modeled using game theory. Some new wrinkles: infinite action space imperfect information about payoffs (other agents' valuations) How do sellers choose the particular auctions they do? mechanism design: "inverse game theory"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second-Price Auctions</head><p>An auction that might initially seem strange: second-price 1. all bidders submit sealed bids 2. the high bid wins 3. the winner pays the second-highest bid amount Theorem: it is a dominant strategy in a second-price auction to bid your true value for the good. Proof:</p><p>Case 1: bidding truthfully would make you the high bidder you can't gain by changing your bid Case 2: bidding truthfully would not make you the high bidder you can't gain by changing your bid</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second-Price Auctions</head><p>Theorem: it is a dominant strategy in a secondprice auction to bid your true value for the good. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the internet commuters choosing the fastest route home users sharing files P2P students deciding which job skills to learn businesses choosing where to locate Action-Graph Games set of players:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Case 1: bidding truthfully, you're the high bidder bid more: no difference (still win, pay same)</figDesc><table>bid less: 

1. no difference 
2. you lose 

$0 

$20 

$40 

$60 

$80 

$100 

$120 

your bid 
next-highest bid 

you pay 

true value 

winner pays 

winner 
winner 
</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Second-Price Auctions</head><p>Theorem: it is a dominant strategy in a secondprice auction to bid your true value for the good. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
