<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Estimating Bidders&apos; Valuation Distributions in Online Auctions</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Albert</forename><forename type="middle">Xin</forename><surname>Jiang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of British Columbia</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Leyton-Brown</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Computer Science</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">University of British Columbia</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Estimating Bidders&apos; Valuation Distributions in Online Auctions</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:32+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>• Game Theoretic Approach <ref type="bibr">[Milgrom &amp; Weber, 1982]</ref>, much subsequent work from econ.</p><p>-model the situation as a Bayesian game -compute and then play a Bayes-Nash equilibrium of the game • when other bidders' valuations are not known, estimate them from history -drawbacks:</p><p>• rationality of other agents may be in doubt • intractability of computing equilibrium • multiple equilibria • Decision Theoretic Approach <ref type="bibr">[Boutilier et al. 1999;</ref><ref type="bibr">Byde 2002;</ref><ref type="bibr">Stone et al. 2003;</ref><ref type="bibr">Greenwald &amp; Boyan 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">MacKie-Mason et al. 2004;</ref><ref type="bibr">Osepayshvili et al. 2005]</ref> -learn the behavior of other bidders from historical data • treat other bidders as part of the environment -play an optimal strategy in the resulting single-agent decision problem • let n denote the number of bidders who place (accepted) bids in the auction -each bidder i has an independent private valuation drawn from distribution f(v)</p><p>• Bidding dynamics -start with reserve price of zero -bidders sequentially place proxy bids (each bidder gets only one bid) -auctioneer maintains current price: second-highest proxy amount declared so far -if a new bid is less than the current price, it is dropped • Bidding history -some bidders' proxy bid amounts will be perfectly observed (denote this set of bids x o )</p><p>• any bidder who placed a proxy bid and was outbid (n-1 such bidders) -however, some bids will be hidden (denote this set x h )</p><p>• highest bid (one bidder) -revealed only up to the second-highest bidder's proxy amount • any bid which was lower than the current price when it was placed (m -n bidders)</p><p>-either the bidder leaves or the bid is rejected Bidding Example Learning the Distributions f(v) and g(m)</p><p>• Data: a set of auction histories -number of bidders and bids distributed identically in each auction • Simple technique for estimating f(v) and g(m):</p><p>-ignore hidden bids, considering only x o and n from each auction -use any standard density estimation technique to learn the distributions -essentially this is the straightforward price estimation technique described earlier</p><p>• Problem:</p><p>-the simple technique ignores the hidden bids and so introduces bias g(m) will be skewed towards small values because n ≤ m f(v) may be</p><p>• skewed towards small values because it ignores the winning bid • skewed towards large values because ignores dropped, losing bids EM Algorithm</p><p>• Solution: use EM to account for hidden bids -similar in spirit to the approach described above by Boutilier et al. <ref type="bibr">(1999)</ref> -however, in our setting some losing bids are also hidden; the number of bidders is uncertain; expected number of hidden bids depends on x o and f(v)</p><p>• E step: generate the missing data given estimates of f', g' and bidding model -for each observation x o , repeat until N samples of x h have been generated:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">• sample m from g'(m | m ≥ n)</formula><p>• simulate bidding process until mn + 1 bids have been generated: is the EU of the bidding strategy that maximizes U j+1 (derived in the paper)</p><p>• first term: payoff from current auction; second term: payoff from future auctions • note that U j+1 depends on the distribution of the highest bid:</p><p>• …and that F j 1 depends in turn on f(v), g(m)</p><p>• thus we must estimate f(v), g(m) to build a decision theoretic agent in this setting • Our agent computes U * j+1 by approximating an integral using Monte Carlo sampling, again relying on our model of the auction Elaborations • Auctions that overlap in time -note that while the optimal bid in auction j does not depend on f j 1 , it does depend on f l 1 for l &gt; j -If an auction l receives a set of (observed) bids b l before auction j has ended, we can compute a posterior estimate of f l 1 (v), and thus a better bid for auction j</p><p>• sample from f l 1 (v) by simulating auction l according to our auction model</p><p>• What about the game theoretic approach?</p><p>-If each bidder (other than our agent) only participates in one auction:</p><p>• dominant strategy is to bid truthfully: b(v) = v • we can use the decision-theoretic approach -If other bidders participate in more than one auction <ref type="bibr">[Milgrom &amp; Weber, 1982]</ref> • equilibrium strategy gets more complex (both strategically and computationally) -depends on entry, exit policies of other agents -If we have to estimate f and g, presumably other agents do too. How should we account for the possibility that they will learn incorrect distributions?</p><p>• success in this domain is much harder to benchmark experimentally -do we believe that all agents will follow an equilibrium strategy on eBay? Experiments • We compared our EM approach against the simple approach I. Synthetic data: sequence of auctions for identical items, known distribution families II. Synthetic data: sequence of auctions for non-identical items, known distribution families III. Synthetic data: sequence of auctions for identical items, unknown distribution families IV. eBay data: auctions for Playstation 2, March 2005.</p><p>• For each dataset, we ask two questions: -EM approach consistently has lower KL divergence than the simple approach -statistically significant difference: Wilcoxon sign-rank test (non-parametric)  -EM, simple approaches estimating normal and Poisson distributions -EM, simple approaches using kernel density estimation • Question 1: no ground truth for this data set-dropped bids are really dropped, etc.</p><p>• Question 2: the EM approaches achieve significantly higher expected payoffs than the simple approaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion &amp; Future Work</head><p>• Bidding agents in online auction settings face the problem of estimating -distribution of bid amounts; -distribution of number of bidders from incomplete auction data • We proposed a learning approach based on EM</p><p>• We considered the application of building a decision theoretic agent for sequences of online auctions • We showed in experiments that our EM approach never did worse and usually did better than the straightforward approach, on both synthetic and real-world data • Thank you for your attention!</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Draw a sample from f'(v) to represent a new bid -If the sampled bid exceeds the next bid in x o , replace the bid with the next bid from x o . Otherwise, add the sampled bid to x h • if x h does not contain exactly one bid that exceeds the highest bid in x o , reject sample • M step: -update f '(v) and g'(m) to maximize the likelihood of the bids x o ∪ x h• depends on functional form of f', g'; either analytic or using e.g. approach described above is decision-theoretic • What if we want to take a game-theoretic approach?-Athey &amp; Haile, (2000) discuss estimation in the game theoretic setting • however, they generally assume that number of bidders is known -brief discussion of unknown number of bidders, but not relevant to our online auction setting -let f(v) be the distribution of bidder's valuations (instead of bid amounts) • g(m) remains the distribution of number of bidders, as before -given a bidder's valuation v, what is his bid amount? • solve for Bayes-Nash equilibrium of the auction game: bid function b(v |f, g) • EM algorithm to estimate f and g in a GT setting: -E step: for each sample given observation x o : • sample m from g'(m | m ≥ n) • compute observed bidders' valuations v o from x o by inverting the bid function • generate new bidders with valuations v h who place hidden bids x h = b(v h |f', g') -simulate the auction until mn + 1 bids are generated, where exactly one hidden bid is higher than the highest observed bid -M step: update f' and g' to maximize likelihood of the valuations v o ∪ v h the construction of a decision-theoretic agent to participate in a finite sequence of auctions (under our online auction model) -given estimates f'(v) and g'(m), what are the optimal bidding strategies? • Auction environment -k sequential, single-good online auctions for possibly non-identical goods -we want only one item • e.g. buying a Playstation 2 from eBay, where such auctions are held regularly -denote our valuation for the item in auction j as v j and our bid as b j -let U j denote expected payoff at time j, conditional on not having won already • a function of our valuations for the goods in the auctions j, …, k • Greenwald &amp; Boyan (2004) and Arora et al. (2003) analyzed similar domains -using similar reasoning, we derive the optimal bidding strategy for</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Which approach gives better estimates of the distributions f(v), g(m), f 1 (v)? 2. Which approach gives better expected payoffs under the decision-theoretic bidding model? Data: f(v) is a normal distribution; g(m) is a Poisson distribution • Bidding history of 40 auctions is generated for each instance. • Both learning approaches use the correct (normal &amp; Poisson) families of distributions to estimate f(v) and g(m) • Question 1: which approach made a better estimate of f(v), g(m), f 1 (v)?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of eight new auctions, after learning from the 40-auction history -in the new auctions, we still use the true g(m) and f(v)• Question 2: following the optimal strategy with the EM estimates gives higher expected payoffs than following this strategy with the simple approach'mean of f(v) depends linearly on some unknown parameter a • Both approaches use linear regression to estimate the linear coefficients • Question 1: EM approach gives (stat. significantly) better estimates • Question 2: EM approach achieves significantly better expected payoffs</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Learning Valuation/Price Distributions • Whether the GT or DT approach is taken, a shared subproblem is using historical data to estimate distribution of bidders' bid amounts or valuations for the case where these sequential auctions are repeated, discusses learning a distribution of other agents' highest bid for each good, based on winning bids• uses EM: the agent's own bid wins, hiding the highest bid by other agents</figDesc><table>• [Athey &amp; Haile, 2000], various other papers in econometrics: 

-assume that bidders are perfectly rational and follow equilibrium strategies 
-estimation of valuation distributions in various auction types given observed bids 

• [Byde, 2002], [Stone et al. 2003], [Greenwald &amp; Boyan, 2004], 
[MacKie-Mason et al. 2004], [Osepayshvili et al. 2005]: 

-estimate the distribution of the final prices in (e.g.) English auctions 
based on selling price and number of agents 

• [Boutilier et al. 1999]: 

-a decision-theoretic MDP approach to bidding in sequential first-price auctions 
for complementary goods 
-1. Background 

2. Online Auction Model and Learning Problem 

3. Bidding in Sequential Auctions 

4. Experimental Evaluation 

Online Auction Model 

• A (possibly repeated) online English auction such as eBay 

-m potential bidders, with m drawn from a distribution g(m) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="false"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Data Set III: Unknown distributions • Identical items. Distribution families for f(v) and g(m) are unknown -ground truth: f(v) is Gamma distributed; g(m) is a mixture of two Poissons • Use kernel density estimation to estimate f(v) and g(m) • Result: the EM approach gives better estimates (significantly lower KL divergence); both approaches achieved similar payoffs (difference not significant) Data Set IV: eBay Data • 60 Sony Playstation-2 auctions from eBay, March 2005 -considered only one-day auctions with at least 3 bidders • Problem: highest bids not available • Workaround: "pretend" second-highest bid is the highest bid -justification: this "shifted" data set should have similar characteristics to the actual bidding history • Compared four approaches:</figDesc><table>−10 
−5 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
0 

0.01 

0.02 

0.03 

0.04 

0.05 

0.06 

0.07 

0.08 

0.09 

Bid Amount 

Distribution of Highest Bid 

true 
simple kernel 
EM kernel 

simple 

simple kernel 
EM 
EM kernel 

0 

1 

2 

3 

4 

5 

Regret 

Payoff Regrets 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
