<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /mnt/sda1/Dissertation/grobid/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Hadronic Decays of Charm</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Kevin</forename><surname>Stenson</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Dept of Physics &amp; Astronomy</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit1">VU Station B351807</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution" key="instit2">Vanderbilt University</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>37235</postCode>
									<settlement>Nashville</settlement>
									<region>TN</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Hadronic Decays of Charm</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2019-12-24T15:33+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Recent hadronic charm decay results from fixed-target experiments are presented. New measurements of the D 0 K ¡ K ¢ K ¡ π ¢ branching ratio are shown as are recent results from Dalitz plot fits to D</p><p>These fits include measurements of the masses and widths of several light resonances as well as strong evidence for the existence of two light scalar particles, the ππ resonance σ and the Kπ resonance κ. ¥ 24 ¦ 23 U 17 MeV/c 2 and Γ σ R 324 ¥ 42 ¦ 40</p><p>U 21 MeV/c 2 . Many checks were made to validate the existence of the σ in this decay. These checks included fitting with a vector and tensor state, and fitting with no phase variation. The fit with a phase-varying scalar particle was clearly preferred.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>INTRODUCTION</head><p>Hadronic decays of charm are rich in information about QCD. For instance, the suppression of D 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">¤ π ¥ π¦ relative to D 0 ¤ K ¦ K ¥</formula><p>proved the importance of final state interactions in charm decays. Also, hadronic decays give rise to the 2.5 § difference between the D ¥ and D 0 lifetimes. Hadronic decays can provide information on relative strengths of decay diagrams (spectator, exchange, annihilation, etc.). Spectator diagrams are believed to be responsible for the vast majority of the charm decay rate. In a spectator diagram, the charm quark decays while the other quark in the meson is a spectator. By contrast, exchange and annihilation diagrams require a connection between the charm quark and the other quark in the meson and are therefore suppressed. Determining the contributions of these diagrams is an interesting open question in charm physics.</p><p>More recently, charm has been used to investigate the light resonances which are products of charm decays. Although very high statistics scattering experiments have been performed for many years to investigate these resonances, many parameters are still virtually unknown. Charm offers a unique way to investigate these resonances by nature of its low background and well defined initial state (pseudoscalar meson).</p><p>Experimentally, hadronic decays can be investigated by comparing branching ratios and by analyzing the resonant structure of multibody decays. The results presented here come from the Fermilab experiments E791 and FOCUS. E791 (FOCUS) ran in 1991 (1996-7) with a 500 GeV/c 2 π¦ beam (180 GeV photon beam) on five (four) targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BRANCHING RATIO MEASUREMENTS</head><p>Calculations of charm quark decay rates via the weak interaction have been possible for many years. Unfortunately, only charm hadron decay rates (which are affected by the strong force) can be measured by experiments. The strong force is even more intimately involved when the charm particle decays into hadrons. Thus, deviations from the naïve weak prediction for a given decay can provide insight into the nature of the strong force.   </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Mass(K − K + K − π + ) Mass(K − K + K − π + ) Mass(K − K + K − π + ) GeV/</formula><formula xml:id="formula_2">Mass(K − π + π − π + ) Mass(K − π + π − π + ) Mass(K − π + π − π + ) GeV/c 2 Events / 5 MeV/c 2 Mass(K − π + π − π + )</formula><p>Kπππ Yield = 59228 ± 276 FOCUS preliminary FIGURE 1. E791 and FOCUS signals from</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">D 0 K ¡ K ¢ K ¡ π ¢ and D 0 K ¡ π ¢ π¡ π ¢ decays. D 0 @ K A K B K A π B branching ratio The decays D 0 ¤ K ¦ K ¥ K ¦ π ¥ and D 0 ¤ K ¦ π ¥ π¦ π ¥</formula><p>are both Cabibbo favored decays. A Cabibbo-favored hadronic D 0 C cūD decay produces one s quark from the charm, oneū spectator quark, and a u andd quark from the virtual W. If both decay modes were entirely non-resonant, forming the K ¦ π ¥ π¦ π ¥ final state would require popping uūdd from the vacuum while K</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">¦ K ¥ K ¦ π ¥</formula><p>would require uūss and the branching ratio between D 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">¤ K ¦ K ¥ K ¦ π ¥ and D 0 ¤ K ¦ π ¥ π¦ π ¥</formula><p>could be used to determine the ss suppression relative to dd. Multi-body charm decays generally proceed through resonances, however, which complicates the issue. Even in this case, one can note that the D 0 ¤ K ¦ π ¥ π¦ π ¥ decay can occur through resonances using only the four quarks from the decay, e.g. K</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">E C 892D 0 C sdD ρ C 770D 0 C uūD , while the D 0 ¤ K ¦ K ¥ K ¦ π ¥</formula><p>decay requires either an ss pair from the vacuum or a final state interaction which couples ππ to KK. The recent E791 result contains some of these speculations <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">[1]</ref>. Signals for these two modes from E791 and FOCUS are shown in <ref type="figure">Fig. 1</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DALITZ PLOT ANALYSES</head><p>Multibody decays of charm particles can occur through various strong resonances which can interfere with each other. In a three-body decay, a "Dalitz" plot can be constructed to show the effect of these resonances and their interferences by plotting the squared invariant mass of two combinations of the final state particles against each other. In the absence of interference, how a resonance appears on the Dalitz will depend on its mass and width (a relativistic Breit-Wigner) as well as on its spin (Legendre polynomials). Interference effects can significantly alter these shapes. Fitting a Dalitz plot to a fully coherent sum of resonances allows one to extract information about how much each resonance contributes and how each resonance interferes with other resonances. By performing a coherent Dalitz plot analysis one can extract information about weak decays and the effects of the strong force on the weak decays. </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">¡ £ ¢ ¤ ¥ § ¦¨ © " ! $ # % ' &amp; ( 0 ) 2 1 4 3 5 7 6 9 8 @ 6 B A C 6 7 D ' ! # F E ! # FIGURE 2. Preliminary D ¢ K ¡ K ¢ π ¢</formula><p>FOCUS Dalitz plot and projections. Projections show the data background, data signal+background, and the fitted result. </p><formula xml:id="formula_8">K H P I 892Q K ¢ 22R 0 S 1R 1 0 (fixed) a 0 I 980Q π ¢ 27R 8 S 4R 8 146 S 5 φI 1020Q π ¢ 27R 8 S 0R 9 244 S 6 f 2 I 1270Q π ¢ 0R 7 S 0R 2 12 S 7 f 0 I 1370Q π ¢ 5R 9 S 1R 2 60 S 6 K H I 1410Q K ¢ 8R 8 S 1R 9 135 S 6 K H 0 I 1430Q K ¢ 69R 3 S 6R 3 63 S 4 φI 1680Q π ¢ 1R 5 S 0R 5 T 70 S 9 sum 163.8 D B @ K A K B π B decays</formula><p>FOCUS has a high statistics sample of the singly Cabibbo suppressed decay D</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">¥ ¤ K ¦ K ¥ π ¥ .</formula><p>The Dalitz plot as well as projections along each axis for this mode are shown in    </p><formula xml:id="formula_10">1/ C m 2 m 2 r ¡ im r Γ r C m 2 D D</formula><p>for a resonance r with a mass and width of m r and Γ r , respectively and at a two-body mass-squard of m 2 . In the f 0</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">C 980D WA92 coupled channel formula, Γ r is replaced with Γ π r ¡ Γ K r where Γ π r C m 2 D R g π ¢ m 2 ππ £ 4 m 2 π and Γ K r C m 2 D R g K F ¥ ¤ m 2 ππ £ 4 m 2 KI ¡ ¤ m 2 ππ £ 4 m 2 K 0 P .</formula><p>This framework yields . In their initial fit to the Dalitz plot using all known resonances, the fit quality was very poor with a confidence level of 10¦ 5 . By including a low mass scalar particle (σ) the fit was significantly improved and yielded a confidence level of 75%, providing strong evidence for the elusive light scalar. The results from both fits are tabulated in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 3</ref>. From the fit, the σ parameters were determined to be M σ </p><formula xml:id="formula_12">M f 0 ¦ 980 § R 977 U 3 U 2 MeV/c 2 , g π R 0T 09 U 0T 01 U<label>0T</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">D B @ K A π B π B The Cabibbo favored decay D ¥ ¤ K ¦ π ¥ π ¥</formula><p>provides a very high statistics mode in which to study charm decays. Previous analyses of this decay <ref type="bibr" target="#b7">[8,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b8">9]</ref> have identified two mysteries in this decay. The first mystery is why there is a dominant non-resonant contribution; unique in charm decays. The second mystery is why a good fit to this Dalitz plot seems to be impossible to achieve. The E791 data sample of 15,090 events (94% signal) can be used to shed light on these mysteries. Fitting the data using all known resonances results in a large non-resonant contribution and a very poor fit (confidence level of 10¦ 11 ), similar to past attempts. Given the evidence for the σ in the D ¥ ¤ π ¥ π¦ π ¥ mode, an additional scalar (κ) was added to the D</p><formula xml:id="formula_14">¥ ¤ K ¦ π ¥ π ¥</formula><p>fit. This provides a dramatic reduction in the non-resonant contribution (from 91% to 13%) and a much improved fit (confidence level of 95%). The preliminary results of both fits are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 4</ref>. The preliminary κ parameters are found to be M κ 12 MeV/c 2 ) have also been extracted in this analysis <ref type="bibr" target="#b9">[10]</ref>.     </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>In the Dalitz plot and on the m 2 C KKD projection, a very clear φ C 1020D can be seen. The K E C 892D across the Dalitz plot and along the m 2 C KπD projection is also clear. Both contributions show a cos θ modulation of the amplitude due to the spin-1 nature of the resonances. Distortions due to interferences are also visible. Preliminary fit results from a fully coherent analysis of the data are tabulated inTable 1. These results support the presence of significant amounts of K explains the broad enhancement at high m 2 C KπD . The existance of many resonances with very different phases indicates significant interferences, as does the fact that the fit fraction sum is much greater than 100%. These interferences explain the obvious distortions seen in the Dalitz plot. Work is currently underway to investigate direct CP violation by comparing the Dalitz plots of the D ¥ and D¦ decays. While for two-body decays a simple branching ratio is sufficient, for multi-body modes a Dalitz plot analysis is necessary to extract all of the information on direct CP violation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>FIGURE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Diagram of annihilation (left) and resonance (right) contributions to D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>FIGURE 4 .FOCUS</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Preliminary Dalitz plot and projections. Projections show the data background, data signal+background, and the fitted result. favored, it can only occur via a spectator diagram if it uses a resonance which couples to both KK and ππ or via final state interactions. It can also proceed via an annihilation diagram. These possibilities are sketched in Fig. 3. Since ρ C 770D does not couple to KK, any ρ C 770D would indicate an annihilation diagram contribution or final state interactions. A resonance known to couple to KK and ππ is the f 0 C 980D . This mysterious state has been proposed as a four-quark state and KK molecule among other things. The presence of the a 0 C 980D further complicates the understanding of this unique resonance. The f 0 C980D mass is below the KK threshold but is broad enough to have a significant branching fraction to KK even with limited phase space.The FOCUS Dalitz plot and projections for D also visible. The results of a preliminary fit to this distribution as well as E791 results<ref type="bibr" target="#b2">[3]</ref> are shown inTable 2. Both results clearly show f 0 C 980D dominance and no significant ρ C 770D . Thus, this decay proceeds almost entirely through resonance modes with no evidence of an annihilation diagram contribution.Using data, E791 and FOCUS have made measurements of the poorly measured scalars contributing to the D and width measurements from 1973 to the present, with 13 measurements in 1999 alone, there is still no consensus on either value. The I=0, J=0 states betweeen 1200 and 1500 MeV/c 2 are even more murky.E791 finds a mass and width of the f /c 2 , respectively. FOCUS uses S 0 C 1475D for a scalar around 1475 MeV/c 2 , as seen in an E687 analysis. The preliminary mass and width are found to be 1473U 8 MeV/c 2 and 112 U 17 MeV/c 2 , respectively; quite comparable to the E791 result for f 0 C 1370D .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the E791 data. Fitting with a standard Breit-Wigner results in minor changes: the K-matrix framework works quite well in dealing with the coupled channel nature of the f 0 C 980D<ref type="bibr" target="#b4">[5,</ref><ref type="bibr" target="#b5">6]</ref>. In this framework, transformed variables are used: ρ ππ and ρ KK are phase space terms and γ ππ and γ KK are coupling constants normalized to γ</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>/c 2 . Attempts to explain the data in other ways (e.g. including a vector state, tensor state, non-phase-varying state, structured non-resonant contribution) have been inadequate. Preliminary meausrements of the K</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>FIGURE 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>FOCUS Dalitz plots and projections for D the data background, data signal+background, and the fitted result.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>TABLE 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Preliminary FOCUS Dalitz plot fit results for D</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="false"><head>TABLE 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Preliminary FOCUS Dalitz plot fit results for the decay D</figDesc><table>¢ 

K 

¡ 

K 

¢ 

π 

¢ 

. (Statistical errors only.) 

Decay mode 
Fraction (%) 
Phase (G ) 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="false"><head>TABLE 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>E791 [3] and preliminary FOCUS Dalitz plot fit results for the decay D ¢ . Errors on FOCUS results are statistical only. 980D . A standard relativistic Breit-Wigner is proportional to</figDesc><table>¢ 

s 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false"><head>TABLE 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>E791 Dalitz plot fit results for the decay D eter errors from "without σ" fits are statistical only.</figDesc><table>¢ 

π 

¢ 

π¡ π 

¢ 

[7]. Param-
</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false"><head>TABLE 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Preliminary E791 Dalitz plot fit results for the decay D . Parameter errors from "without κ" fits are statistical only. Without κ: CL = 10¡ 11With κ: CL = 95%</figDesc><table>¢ 

K 

¡ 

π 

¢ 

π 

¢ 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aitala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">112003</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Frabetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">354</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">486</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aitala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">765</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Groom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Eur. Phys. J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">D-Meson Dalitz Fit from Focus</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Malvezzi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Intersections of Particle and Nuclear Physics: 7th Conference</title>
		<editor>Z. Parsa and W. J. Marciano</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Institute of Physics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2000" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">549</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">U</forename><surname>Chung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1995" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">404</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>Ann Physik</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Aitala</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">770</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anjos</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Rev</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">46</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">56</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1993" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Frabetti</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Phys. Lett</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">331</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">217</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1994" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Light Meson Physics from Charm Decays at Fermilab E791</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">C</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">IX International Conference on Hadron Spectroscopy</title>
		<editor>D. Amelin</editor>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>American Institute of Physics</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
